<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The divine catastrophe of the kingly family of the house of Stuarts or, a short history of the rise, reign, and ruine thereof. Wherein the most secret and chamber-abominations of the two last kings are discovered, divine justice in King Charles his overthrow vindicated, and the Parliaments proceedings against him clearly justified, by Sir Edward Peyton, knight and baronet, a diligent observer of those times.</title>
            <author>Peyton, Edward, Sir, 1588?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1291_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867900</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 173:E1291[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The divine catastrophe of the kingly family of the house of Stuarts or, a short history of the rise, reign, and ruine thereof. Wherein the most secret and chamber-abominations of the two last kings are discovered, divine justice in King Charles his overthrow vindicated, and the Parliaments proceedings against him clearly justified, by Sir Edward Peyton, knight and baronet, a diligent observer of those times.</title>
                  <author>Peyton, Edward, Sir, 1588?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 149, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the black Spread-Eagle at the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The rise, reign, and ruine of the House of Stuarts.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 24.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Divine Catastrophe</hi> OF The KINGLY Family Of the Houſe of <hi>ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARTS:</hi> OR, A SHORT HISTORY OF THE Riſe, Reign, and Ruine Thereof.</p>
            <p>Wherein the moſt ſecret and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-abominations of the two laſt Kings are diſcovered, Divine Juſtice in King <hi>Charles</hi> his overthrow vindicated, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments proceedings againſt him clearly juſtified,</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>Edward Peyton</hi> Knight and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet, a diligent obſerver of Thoſe Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle at the weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:169723:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169723:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>Supreme Authoritie</hi> of this Nation, Aſſembled in this preſent PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right honorable Senators,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Andering in the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of my contemplations, to finde out what was most ſutable to preſent to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of Parliament, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a Divine revolution as God hath
<pb facs="tcp:169723:3"/>brought to paſs inſtrumentally by your wiſdom and direction, and his heavenly Providence; in this wide field, the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent guided my thoughts to dedicate a Diſcourſe to your honourable hands, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fatal <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of the laſt Houſe had Superintendencie over us, to the time the Almighty put the Stern of this Commonwealth into a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Power, which I moſt humbly wiſh our celeſtial Creator to continue, till a Snail be able to creep over the whole Globe of the earth.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, I crave your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that I have not ſo diſtinctly in order laid down many remarkable paſſages wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy recite, my Papers being remote a great diſtance from me: yet, by Gods grace, I have compoſed a little <hi>Enchiridion</hi> of divers remarkable events have happened out, to prove Gods juſt revenging hand on the Family of the Kingly <hi>Stuarts</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and juſtified your proceedings,
<pb facs="tcp:169723:3"/>and proved that the heavie weight of ſin hath given a downfal juſtly impoſed by Providence from above; my Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reaching no higher then from the King of <hi>Scots</hi> being taken priſoner at <hi>Muſcleborough</hi>-field, in <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his Reign.</p>
            <p>Now therefore I thrice humbly deſire your Patronage, eſpecially finding by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience the compoſition and ſtile of this preſent Narrative will incur the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and hatred of moſt in this State: yet I value it not, being prompt by a higher power then that of Man, which points out by a Divine finger the overthrow of all men exalted above all that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God, whoſe ruine will be the bridge to let into the Stage of the world the heavenly Government of Chriſt, which ſhall continue for ever, maugre the malice of the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I moſt humbly implore the thrice honourable Parliament to accept of
<pb facs="tcp:169723:4"/>This, as a teſtimony of my fidelity to the preſent Government; which I pray God to bleſs and maintain, to advance his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and bring the whole Nation to a moſt happie condition, which now the preſent ſymptomes thereof ſhew plainly a new ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of a great tranquillity, not onely to this, but to the three Nations in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edw. Peyton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169723:4"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Riſe, Reign and Ruine</hi> OF THE Kingly Family Of the STUARTS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince <hi>Great Britain</hi> hath been elevated all along the ſtems of <hi>Plantagenet, Theodor</hi> or <hi>Tedor,</hi> and <hi>Stuart,</hi> to ſo high a Tree of Tyranny as ſhe was afore the late wars; the Princes had deſignes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to a way of making
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169723:5"/>themſelves abſolute Governours; which overture hath appeared more or leſs, according to the humour of times, and inclination of the Guiders of the Stern: for ſome indued with ability and craftineſs neceſſary to ſettle an uſurped ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whilſt the people were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to beare the load of that bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, have made a progreſs ſo poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickly to bring their aims to the mark ſhot at, that they have ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly diſſembled the enterpriſe, as no notice or ſcandal arrived at their doors, nor impatience to the three Countreys of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and (ſince the acceſs of the Family of the <hi>Stuarts</hi>) to <hi>Scotland;</hi> until King <hi>James,</hi> for hatred of his Mothers death, plotted the ruine of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which ratified Queen <hi>Maries</hi> execution; and left it as his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his ſucceſſor to follow; dictating, not long afore his death,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169723:5"/>to <hi>Williams</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> the courſe he ſhould ſteer to bring his counſel to concluſion. This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſh advice thruſt on this wilful Prince with an inconſiderate fury; and, inflamed with that fire, to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to himſelf and his ſucceſſors an unbridled power of dominion; which hurried him on with the whirlwinde of paſſion, to diſcover the myſtery which ought to have been concealed till the deſigne ſhould be accompliſhed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, of this number in our days was <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, who, from the beginning of his Government, blaming the moderation of his predeceſſors, reſolved to go a way contrary to the ſtream of a pious Rule, and the command of God; and act, during his time, that which God would not ſuffer to be done in many ages paſt. And becauſe the pretention is always encumbed,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169723:6"/>when the object cannot be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; by wicked advice perceiving he had not ſo well marched to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his drifts, with the juſt power of Parliaments, which might found a Trumpet in the behalf of a Commonwealth, by advice of his Antecedent and his wicked adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, laboured to raze out the memory, breaking up two Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and not ſatified therewith, to practiſe Tyranny, kept the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neer fourteen yeers without ſuch moſt lawful Aſſemblies, where the Rights of the Nation might be diſcovered, and true Liberty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. This he did, that the power of Law, and property of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects eſtates, might be incloſed in his ſole Arbitrary breſt. To that purpoſe, he made his Sycophants of the Council-Table, Judges of the Right of his people, the Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Executioners of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169723:6"/>will, and the High-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion the deſtroyers of Piery and Religion: which three though he revoked by Acts, yet being angry with himſelf for ſo doing, he raiſed a War, to make abortive all he had done, by an armed power, although he ſeemed willing to affect it afore: therefore, purſuing the former ſeries of his will for a Law, <hi>Charles</hi> quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels firſt with the Gentry and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple about Coat, Conduct, and Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money, and plotted with his wicked Council that a thouſand <hi>Germane</hi> Horſe, in the nature of <hi>Trayle Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun,</hi> ſhould take every one denied to give him money, or that would not ſubſcribe to his endleſs will and eaſeleſs power, to be hurried to Priſon, there to end their days; (ſome of them being ſo barbarouſly uſed.) This unjuſt reſolution he took upon him, unleſs they yeelded to his unſatiable deſires: by which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169723:7"/>means, the eyes of many of the triple Nations were ſealed, as pigeons are uſed for traines to devouring Hawks to plume and prey on. This ſtruck ſuch a Pannick fear, that they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined all power conſiſted in the Diadem, to be at his mercy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were ignorant of their Rights, which were uſually diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in Parliaments, by ſome pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the Records. But behold! God raiſed up ſome Heroes within the doors of the Repreſentative, and without, to awaken the people from a dead ſleep; or rather, to cure them of a diſeaſe of lethargy: who rouzing like Lions let looſe out of a Den, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed this moſt wicked Oppreſſion; by which way, they certainly fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods determination upon the ſeventh Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> (being Sabbattical) ſince the beginning of the world, to bring down the Mountain of Monarchy,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169723:7"/>which had continued more then five hundred yeers; to depreſs the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion practiſed in <hi>Europe</hi> from <hi>Charlemain</hi>'s Age; a Symptome and Harbinger for <hi>France, Spaine, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Turky,</hi> and <hi>Papacy,</hi> to change from an unbridled power, to an Ariſtocratical, or Plebeian way of rule, which will better advance the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt thorow the Univerſe: whereby it appeares, that <hi>England,</hi> (by Gods aſſiſtance) may be the elder brother, to bring to paſs ſo mighty an alteration on the the ſtage of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>By divers ungodly Sophiſms of State, for the ſpace of ten yeers, King <hi>Charles</hi> raiſed up innumerable Projectors and ungodly burdens, to enthral the Nations, by an Arbitrary way; impoſing Monopolies &amp; many unlawful Taxes, under which they remained without remedy of relief; the eyes and eares of all in high au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169723:8"/>being blinde and deaf, not to hear nor ſee Petitions of juſt complaints, inſomuch that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple generally cried out, Where are our Laws? and demanded if all Juſtice were baniſhed out of their quarters; and, with eyes lift up to Heaven, deſired that thoſe caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers might not ſwell too big, like a Spleen, to bring a Conſumption to the whole body; praying alſo that their empty purſes might not be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with blood, although their eyes with tears.</p>
            <p>Now this miſerable condition (perceived by the wrinkles ſorrow made on the brow of our diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed affaires, all wiſe counſels baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the reputation of a pious State withered) was augmented by King <hi>Charles</hi> his impoſing the Common-Book of Prayer on the Scots (wherein God ſeemed to be deaf a time, for the ſins of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169723:8"/>multiplied againſt the Divine Majeſty; yet at laſt he heard the prayers of the Saints, that the Scotiſh men could not endure this impoſition ſo Diametrically oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Kirk, and diſpoſition of the Nation.)</p>
            <p>This Stratagem was by the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Laud</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> to bring into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Epiſcopal Government, to unite both Kingdoms in one forme of Church, in ſomething agreeable with <hi>Rome,</hi> as a bridge over which he might bring both people to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, to ingratiate himſelf with the Pope for a Cardinals Cap.</p>
            <p>Lo, how <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in this wide field of behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: the intereſt of the King made Will a Law, and the other avoided ſuch a Slavery: the iſſue was, (growing by this Edict obſtinate) they could not endure it. But
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169723:9"/>King <hi>Charles</hi> perſiſted in his wilful determination to finde out this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to work the effects of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation upon; ſo that this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was fitly preſented to his wiſhes, to raiſe an Armed Power to ſubdue them to his unbridled Pleaſure. But when this War exen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated his Coffers for lack of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he was conſtrained, <hi>nolens vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens,</hi> to call a Parliament, by the advice of the fomer wicked Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, who perſwaded him to it; making the King believe that at his pleaſure he might on all accaſions break the neck of ſuch Aſſemblies. In the mean while, the enterpriſe was hatched on the baſis of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety of inclination, by which he might ſet a bone to divide and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne both; becauſe that Nation, by the immenſe bounty of King <hi>James,</hi> was grown exceeding rich; which ſowed ſeeds of envy in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169723:9"/>to oppoſe the <hi>Scot.</hi> But by this Parliament, God (who hath ſole power in ſublunaries) turned this croſs blow to the good of both, to enlarge the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, and for the Liberty of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the errand of my Diſcourſe is not ſolely to ſhew the abuſes of State, but rather by reckoning up a brief Catalogue of ſome, to demonſtrate and delineate the juſt Judgement of God on the Family of theſe <hi>Stuarts,</hi> for Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties and Murthers one of another; that we may raiſe up our praiſes to God, who out of the aſhes of intended ruine, hath made the Source of ſo glorious a State as now is planted on our Engliſh Stage, wherein God findes this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth very conſiſtent with his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equate glory in conſummating the fulneſs of the Gentiles, and calling
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169723:10"/>home of the Jews, foretold in the Scriptures, to be performed in the latter Ages of the World; to the intent Promiſes and Prophecies ſhould be accompliſhed, for the Dominion of Chriſt to extend to the ends of the earth, that thoſe who ſit in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of death, may be brought into a more perſpicuous light, to follow the ſteps Chriſt hath traced out for all to walk in; which the over-grown pride of Kings and Emperours would not ſubmit to.</p>
            <p>Therefore to demonſtrate and obſerve, how the Almighty hand of God hath determined the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of the Royal Stock of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> for murthering one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for their prophane Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and wanton Laſciviouſneſs of thoſe Imps ingrafted in that Stock; I am forced to raiſe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of this Relation higher by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169723:10"/>the fourth Story, and laſt ſtaire of the great Grand-father of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt; who was ſlaine at <hi>Muſcle-borough</hi>-field by the Engliſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, under the command of the Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Surrey.</hi> This King, I ſay, left a ſole Daughter, <hi>Mary Suart,</hi> Inheritrix of that Realm; who, when ſhe attained of Viripotency, was ſought for a conſort to the Dolphin of <hi>France;</hi> which title of right belongs to the firſt Son of the King of that Crown. This Prince, after the Marriage, ended his days by a ſhiver of a Launce, at the ſport of Tourney in <hi>Paris.</hi> A Match contrived by the French, for the Scots to be Goads in our ſides, to hinder our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading of <hi>France,</hi> to which we had a juſt Title.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>Mary</hi> deprived of her mate by this ſad accident, living ſome few yeers in the French Court,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169723:11"/>where ſhe was educated in the School of <hi>Venus,</hi> proved an apt Scholar in that wanton Academy; and affecting in her inclination to be more abſolute in her paſſion of Love to chuſe without controul a Paramour ſutable, when, how long, and who ſhe pleaſed, grew weary of the delights of <hi>Paris,</hi> deſiring vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, returned into <hi>Scotland,</hi> where ſhe had more power; ſhe being conſtant in nothing but in Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy: A place where the amorous way was much in eſteeme, though the Church-Government ſomewhat hindered it; which was then not of ſuch force as ſince.</p>
            <p>This Princeſs caſt her glances everywhere about, to finde a beauty fit for her imbrace; and at laſt fixt her liking on the Lord <hi>Darnel,</hi> of the Houſe and Family of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> of <hi>Boote</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> whoſe Anceſtors were there famous, conteſting long
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169723:11"/>ago for the King with one <hi>Wallis</hi> in their home-bred broiles, who ſided with the people. To ſay truth, this Lord was a goodly and amiable perſon, fit for any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peerſhip, how great ſoever: but after ſome time, this Princeſs (ſoon ſatiated) grew weary of the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by reaſon of a ſervant ſhe entertained, called <hi>David Ritſoe,</hi> an Italian Muſician, who exceled in the Airs of <hi>Italy</hi> above others in that Faculty: who inchanting the Queen with his voice, made her think there was no happineſs but in his approach into her Cabinet (a place wherein ſhe continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided:) but from thence the Lord <hi>Darnel</hi> was baniſhed above nine months; divorced from her in joy, although he ſought divers means in vaine.</p>
            <p>At laſt, for a medicine to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy his diſcontent, one <hi>Dowglas</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169723:12"/>Phyſick for his cure, to amove <hi>Ritſoe</hi> from the Queen, and put the Lord her husband into her armes. So violent was the Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, that <hi>Ritſoe</hi> was taken from this Princeſs by twelve arrived Lords, and their retinue, who put her into the Lords armes; killing <hi>Ritſoe,</hi> laid his dead body on the ſame trunk was his bed the firſt night he arrived to the Queens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. But there was much adoe, afore this Tragedy was acted. To underſtand this better, this <hi>Dowglas,</hi> an Agent for the twelve baniſhed Lords out of <hi>Scotland</hi> to return, could not effect it, unleſs the Lord <hi>Darnel</hi> undertook the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the former condition, to diſpatch <hi>Ritſoe</hi> from Court. But they being jealous of <hi>Darnels</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, not fixt in other Puntilio's, would not believe him, till, prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his fingers, he wrote an aſſurance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169723:12"/>under his hand with blood, in a paper, really to effect it: which was acted, when the Queen leaned on <hi>Ritſoes</hi> ſhoulder, at the game of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero with the Earl of <hi>Morton</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>Scotland;</hi> who cheriſhed this unlawfull familiarity: a verity juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied on Oath by <hi>Darnel,</hi> and one of the twelve Lords, the Lord <hi>Ruthin,</hi> at his execution on the Scaffold, a place where dying men ſpeak true.</p>
            <p>This Lady very ſorrowful, reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to <hi>Sterlin</hi> Caſtle, ſhortly after was brought abed of King <hi>James;</hi> but took no delight in her husbands company: for the Lord <hi>Bothwel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a new Corrival in her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who both conſented (as <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus</hi> wife with <hi>Sejanus,</hi> after ſhe had been laſcivious with him) to blow up her husbands body with Gun-powder; who was caſt dead on a tree next morning: a ſpectacle made <hi>Scotland</hi> amazed at ſo fearful a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169723:13"/>murder. By this moſt wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, ſhe grew ſo contemptible to her Realm, that ſhe was fain to flee to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for ſuccour: but lo, ſome yeers afore, ſeverall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were here diſcovered, that this <hi>Mary</hi> ſet the Traytors awork to take away our late Queens life; who were afore condemned for Traytors, and ſuffered death: for this <hi>Mary</hi> was the next pretender to the Crown, from <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh: but God prevented it, by her Privy Council (counted the wiſeſt of all <hi>Europe</hi>) who counſelled <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn her, to free <hi>England</hi> from Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt her Perſon. But the ſage Princeſs conjectured, if the death ſhould be by her Edict, it might raiſe the hatred of forraine Princes againſt her; and therefore cauſed the ſentence onely to be ratified by Act of Parliament, the Vote of the whole Realm, inſomuch that a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169723:13"/>mock-Secretary (called <hi>Daviſon</hi>) was choſen to go to <hi>Fotheringham,</hi> where ſhe was rewarded with a Hatchet: a juſt Judgement of God on her.</p>
            <p>After this, King <hi>James</hi> (being about ſixteen yeers old) was crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and had for Tutor one <hi>Bohan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> called amongſt us <hi>Buchanan;</hi> a learned Divine, and wiſe, to train up young Princes; whoſe Books are famous through this part of the world. This prudent Schoolmaſter obſerving the young Prince's facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſigne any Grant for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants without reading, by which means he had pardoned many mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and paſſed other Inſtruments of damnable conſequence to the Commonwealth; in which this Tutor imitated <hi>Theodoſius</hi>'s godly fraud, to diſcerne the hearts of his Courtiers ſoundneſs in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who having taken great pains with the King from his childhood,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169723:14"/>deſired a boon, which King <hi>Iame</hi> was willing to grant; therefore one morning the king going out early a hunting, <hi>Buchanan</hi> brought an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute reſignation of his kingdom, with all Immunities to it; which was ſigned without aſpect. At night, returning from field-ſports, retiring uſually afore ſupper to read ſome profitable Author, which his School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter choſe; all ſhut out of the Cmhaber, <hi>Buchanan</hi> ſate down in the kings Chair, and told him that he was king, giving him the writing to peruſe; which reading, he ſhed tears for his folly; yet <hi>Buchanan</hi> after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him, and charged his Scholar not to ſigne any Grant but what was juſt; and ſo threw the Grant of all <hi>Scotland</hi> into the fire.</p>
            <p>About this time, Queen <hi>Anne</hi> was brought out of <hi>Denmark</hi> for a match; a Lady of a goodly preſence, beautiful eyes, and ſtrong to be joyned with a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169723:14"/>Prince young, and weak in conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; an union unſutable, for a Vira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go to couple with a Spiny and thin Creature; a courſe made her fancy work as a Fat, for to further a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male content; and placed in her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light one Maſter <hi>Stuart,</hi> of the houſe the Earle of <hi>Murry.</hi> His haunting her Chamber too ſedulouſly, bred ſuch a jealouſie in King <hi>Iames,</hi> for to impart his thoughts to Marqueſs <hi>Huntly,</hi> and get diſpatched this <hi>Stuart</hi> out of the way, burning his houſe, and himſelf in it. After whoſe death, the Queen found others to ſatisfie her unruly appetite, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Earle of <hi>Gowry,</hi> a Lord of a comly viſage, good ſtature, and of an attracting allurement; who upon King <hi>Iames</hi> ſuſpition of often ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety with the Queen, converted to the Poyſon of hatred the friendſhip and love of the Earl; cauſing <hi>Ramſey,</hi> after Earl of <hi>Holderneſs,</hi> with others, to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169723:15"/>murther <hi>Gowry</hi> in his own houſe; giving it out for a ſtale, that the Earl with others would have killed him; And to make his falſhood appear odious in ſhape of truth, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the fifth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> a ſolemne day of Thankſgiving for his ſuppoſed delivery; and in this mocked the God of Heaven.</p>
            <p>After this, the Queen entertained into her ſervice one Mr. <hi>Beely</hi> a Dane, to whom ſhe bore an affection; this Gentleman came with her into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and grew more entire in her thoughts; with whom I had a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, to be a Commiſſioner for him in a Grant his Miſtreſs procured for him of King <hi>Iames,</hi> of felons goods in divers Counties; who in great ſecrecie diſcovered to me, he was naturall Father of King <hi>Charls;</hi> but waxing old, the Queen took two proper Gentlemen of the Houſe of <hi>Bohannon</hi> to her ſervice: theſe being
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169723:15"/>partners in her affection, fell out in a Duell, and killed one another for priority in her love.</p>
            <p>Not long after <hi>Gowries</hi> death, Prince <hi>Henry</hi> was born at <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> whereupon, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſent the Earl of <hi>Suſſex</hi> Ambaſſadour, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate this birth, and be Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with a gallant retinue: but <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> being poor, and the king want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money to diſcharge the glory of ſuch a Royal entertainment, the Earl of <hi>Orkney,</hi> a Baſtard of the former king's, pawned his Eſtate in the Iſlands of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to raiſe a great ſum to diſcharge the Chriſtening. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, how King <hi>James</hi> did not onely not diſengage this Morgage, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered this Earle to die in Priſon at <hi>Blackneſs</hi> neer <hi>Edinburgh</hi>-Caſtle: an ingratitude indelible for after-ages to deteſt.</p>
            <p>I omit the Murders, Inchantments, Witcheries, committed by his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169723:16"/>of weight enough, without more, to pull down that Houſe.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed of this congratulation, and conceiving it to be a ſtep to unite <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> in one Government, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> waxing old, ſent a Letter of incouragement to King <hi>James,</hi> to joyn with him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of his Mothers death; who replied, (as the true Copy expreſſed) that he would not fall at difference with <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſince he was now more ſecure in his Throne, then in his Mothers time; intimating he was not ſorry for her amovall; for her life might have procured his ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> after fourty yeers Reign, was moved by her privy Council to ſettle King <hi>Iames</hi> for ſucceſſor: who ſaid, ſhe would not erect a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in her life, for a follower to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect her end. She was a Lady adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Majeſty, Learning, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169723:16"/>Wiſdom, and Piety; yet fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of death; for ſhe hated any word tended to it; as ſhall be manifeſt by <hi>Roger</hi> Lord <hi>North,</hi> when carving one Day at Dinner, the Queen asked what that covered diſh was; he lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the cover, replied, <hi>Madam, it is a Coffin;</hi> a word moved the Queen to anger: <hi>And are you ſuch a fool,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>to give a Pie ſuch a name?</hi> This gave warning to the Courtiers not to uſe any word mentioned her death. But this prudent Prince died after fourty four yeers compleat; and king <hi>James</hi> was proclaimed about the laſt of <hi>March,</hi> 1602. king of <hi>England,</hi> by his privy Council, aſſiſted by the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Lee.</hi> In <hi>May</hi> after, he entered, met with many Nobles and Gentlemen; the Sheriffs attending him in every County from <hi>Berwick:</hi> ſo that there was a general applauſe, and Royal entertainment, at his entrance into
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169723:17"/>the Charter-houſe in <hi>London;</hi> yet ominouſly attended with a great Plague of three thouſand dying in a week in the City. This Union gave a grand expectation of tranquillity to both kingdoms. To effect this better, he called a Parliament laſted ſeven yeers, and raiſed many Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, with great ſums left by his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor; which vaſt treaſure was all beſtowed on the needy <hi>Scots,</hi> who, like Horſe-leeches, ſucked the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer dry; ſo that Honour and Offices were ſet to ſale, to fill the <hi>Scots</hi> purſes, and empty the kingdoms treaſure. This cauſed a by-word, <hi>That the Exchequer reached from Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to Edinburgh.</hi> This was not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to gorge their inſatiable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, but many Monopolies like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were erected, my ſelf after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting thirty two Patents to the Parliament in <hi>decimo octavo Iacobi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen deprived of the night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169723:17"/>Company of a husband, turned her delight to the Prince, whom ſhe reſpected above her other children: finding him too ſerious, diverted him from ſo much intenſiveneſs, to an amorous geſture, in which the Engliſh Court took great pride. To that purpoſe, ſhe initiated him in the Court of <hi>Cupid;</hi> as one night ſhe ſhut him under lock and key in a chamber with a beautiful young Lady now dead; which ſhewed her love to the ſport: indeed, morelikea Bawd; than a diſcreet Mother, who is bound to ſeaſon her children in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, while young, that they may hold the taſte in age: whoſe example, in vertue or vice, might draw a world to follow the pattern. But after, Prince <hi>Henry</hi> fell mortally ſick of a ſuppoſed Fever, but not without ſuſpition of poyſon. A Prince, whom all <hi>Europe</hi> expected to be the promoter of ſome great and famous action, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169723:18"/>his inclination was bent to the Martial art above his yeers, and alſo excelled in matters of State, both in diſcourſe, and choice of ableſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; which he much delighted in, for advice and counſel. This ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in judgement, and dexterity in Souldiery to form Models of any ſort of Battels, ſtirred up king <hi>Iames</hi> to ſuſpect the Prince might depoſe him; eſpecially knowing he was not begot of his body. This cauſed the Lord <hi>Saintcleare,</hi> then Ambaſſadour in <hi>Denmark,</hi> not to be aſhamed to challenge Prince <hi>Henry</hi> to be his own ſon, to <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> there arrived: ſo that by ſome Pill or other the Prince came to his end. This was plainly ſhewed, when he was cut up to be imbalmed, his brain was Liver-hued and putrefied; an argument of poiſon, as was affirmed by a moſt learned Phyſician, <hi>Butler</hi> of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Now king <hi>Iames,</hi> more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169723:18"/>addicted to love males then females, though for complement he viſited Queen <hi>Anne,</hi> yet never lodged with her a night for many yeers. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, <hi>Gundamore</hi> obſerving how king <hi>Iames</hi> was addicted, told him that the Lady <hi>Hatton</hi> would not ſuffer the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> her husband to come into her fore-door, nor he himſelf to come into her back-door. (<hi>Hatton</hi> and <hi>Ely</hi> houſes joyning together, where they dwelt; ſhe denying him a paſſage backward to take air.)</p>
            <p>Now that the fruit of Mortality might declare humane frailty, Queen <hi>Anne,</hi> who had trod ſo many ſtately footings in masks of Court, Beauty fading, ſtrength faling, and youth metamorphoſed to yeers, health to ſickneſs, being haunted with a lingering ſickneſs, which contracted her end. For Doctor <hi>Upton</hi> at his death (not long afore the Queen's) declared a Skeleton being in her
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169723:19"/>womb, proves ſhe was with childe, and that Phyſick had deſtroyed it, and ſo the Skeleton remained; which was laboured to be purged away, but all in vain, rotted in her. Of this Docter there was a jealouſie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing it, for which his paſſage was made to another world, as his tongue to me at his death uttered; who mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried my neer kinſwoman.</p>
            <p>The Queen departed, the King ſold his affections to Sir <hi>George Villi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> whom he would tumble and kiſs as a Miſtreſs. This favourite had erected many Monopolies; who finding Parliaments hindered his profit, cauſed his Maſter to diſſolve thoſe Patents, and break up the Parliament of <hi>decimo octavo;</hi> raiſing a number of Privy Seals, which were borrowed and never paid.</p>
            <p>And to adde to the iniquity of the times, divers Inceſts were then pardoned: inſomuch as two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169723:19"/>who married two ſiſters one after another, got Licenſe at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>market</hi> not to be moleſted in the High-Commiſſion. But above all, a godly Miniſter in <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> was barbarouſly murthered by one <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> whom King <hi>Iames</hi> pardoned. The reaſon of this murther was, for rebuking him of ſwearing, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and whoring.</p>
            <p>At this time were many pious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſilenced by the Biſhops, who inhibited preaching in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon; divers Exerciſes in ſeveral Towns commanded downe: an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion bred much prophaneſs in <hi>England;</hi> king <hi>lames</hi> allowing dancing about May-poles, and ſo winked at breaking the Sabbath; a vice God curſeth everywhere in Scripture.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay more? All im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety was incouraged in ſuch a ſort, that lawful Mariages were divorced
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169723:20"/>or nullified; as namely, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Eſſex</hi> from the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> late General for the Parliament; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the Lord had a defect, and was not able to perform the act of generation; (although the contrary was after proved) to make a gap for <hi>Somerſet's</hi> adultery, by a Nullity which Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> deviſed; a nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name being given for this to his ſon, who was rewarded with Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; and therefore ſtiled by the people, <hi>Sir Nullity Bilſon.</hi> This Biſhop maintained Chriſts perſonal deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into hell: an opinion diſavowed by all Orthodox Divines. And many other falſe opinions were maintained in that age; as, that <hi>Solomon</hi> was damned, an <hi>Amanuenſes</hi> of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>The ſecond example is the Lord <hi>Riches</hi> Lady, named <hi>Penelope;</hi> who was divorced, to make way for the Lo. <hi>Montjoy</hi>'s luſt, Earl of <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169723:20"/>
What ſhall I ſay more? Did not king <hi>Iames</hi> his minions and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorites rule the kingdom in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the king, who were five in number, ſince his approach upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground? to wit, Sir <hi>George Humes</hi> Earl of <hi>Dunbar,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Herbert</hi> after Earl of <hi>Montgomery</hi> and <hi>Pembrook,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Hayes</hi> Earl of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Car</hi> Earl of <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet,</hi> who defiled his hands in <hi>Overbury</hi>'s death; that wicked divorce uſhering the murther. This <hi>Sommer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> being elected of the Council, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his Library onely with twenty Play-books and wanton Romances; and had no other in his Study. A Lord very like to give wiſe counſel! This Lord, with his Lady, were queſtioned for the murther; and the Lieutenant of the Tower, Sir <hi>George Elloways,</hi> was hanged, but for concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it: king <hi>Iames</hi> being willing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169723:21"/>with this accuſation, to make paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for another favorite, which was Sir <hi>George Villiers,</hi> after Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> who by his greatneſs vitiated many gentile and noble vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins in birth, though vitious for yeelding to his luſt; whoſe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs opened the door to allure them more.</p>
            <p>To pleaſe this favorite, King <hi>Iames</hi> gave way for the Duke to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice others to his will. Two exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples I will recite: firſt, the King entertained Sir <hi>Iohn Crafts,</hi> and his Daughter, a beautiful laſs, at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>market,</hi> to ſit at the Table with the King. This he did then, to procure <hi>Buckingham</hi> the eaſier to vitiate her. Secondly, Mrs <hi>Dorothy Gamay,</hi> being a rare creature; King <hi>Iames</hi> carried <hi>Buckingham</hi> to <hi>Gulford,</hi> to have his will on that Beauty: but Sir <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Bacon</hi>'s Sons conveyed her out of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169723:21"/>a window into a private chamber, over the leads, and ſo diſappointed the Duke of his wicked purpoſe. In which cleanly conveyance, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor had a hand, with the Knights Sons. Truly, that day a ſober man was hard to be ſeen, in King, Prince, and Nobles. Moreover, it was an art King <hi>Iames</hi> uſed for theſe favourites, to be ſkreens to decline the hatred of his People; when complained of in Parliament, and when queſtioned, they were ſpunges to be ſqueezed to to fill his Coffers.</p>
            <p>One ſtory I wil relate, more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then the reſt; the king very ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous of death from the contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> wrote a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Pope</hi> that he would tolerate Popery when he brought affaires to his bent in <hi>Great Britaine.</hi> The Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcovered by a lucky chance, to the ſeven yeers Parliament, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169723:22"/>of in the Remonſtrance to the king, he made the Scotiſh Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary own this act, and affirm it was his, and not the kings; promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to take him off at laſt with advancement: but contrary, it occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the Secretaries ruine.</p>
            <p>Here, by the way, I muſt play the Cook, to lard three ſeveral occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences not impertinent to the matter in hand. The firſt was, that Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Winnode</hi> took a bribe of 20000 pound, to redeliver the four Cautio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Townes in <hi>Holland</hi> to the <hi>Dutch;</hi> which we now may ſee might have curbed the States from prejudicing <hi>England.</hi> Another was, king <hi>Iames</hi> his weakneſs, to give way to <hi>Gunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> to take away Sir <hi>Walter Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liegh</hi>'s life; who might have vexed <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Spaine.</hi> A third was, to ſell Iron Ordnance, &amp; diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the art of their Carriages; which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169723:22"/>all the world was ignorant of.</p>
            <p>This laſt favourite, <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> advanced to ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer with his Mother, rewarded the king with poyſon, by a poyſoning water, and a plaiſter made of the Oyle of Toads.</p>
            <p>This Duke, from a private Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman with an annuity of thirty pound a yeer for life, was raiſed to ſuch a mount of glory and power, to be Maſter of Horſe, Maſter of the Wards &amp; Liveries, Admiral of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Lord Warden of the Cinq<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. A Lord tall of ſtature, amiable countenance; who, like a ravenous kyte, ingroſſed all into his hands, to inrich and advance his kindred, and to place and diſplace whom he liſted: ſo that this Lord was grown ſo potent, his Maſter ſtood in awe of him, in ſuch ſort, that when the king was ſick of the Gout,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169723:23"/>he would remove him from place to place at pleaſure, againſt the kings will: who, to work his ends, wrought into favour with the rifing <hi>Phebus,</hi> king <hi>Charles.</hi> The king prying into this way of his Succeſſor, ſet a bold Courtier, Doctor <hi>Turner,</hi> a float, to bring the Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> (then out) to launch into favou; but the Duke complying with <hi>Turner,</hi> perceived the plot againſt him, wrought by a countermine, by <hi>Charles</hi> the chief Engineer: but the Dukes drift was, after king <hi>Iames</hi> his death, to make himſelf king of <hi>Ireland;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was ſtiled Prince of <hi>Typera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> an appendix to that Throne. This made the Duke ſwell like a Toad, to ſuch a monſtrous proportion of greatneſs in vaſt thoughts, as muiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to an ocean, from the rivers of pride, power, and ambition, he ſate as a Gyant on the ſhoulders of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169723:23"/>king <hi>Iames,</hi> and drowned his power; limiting no bounds to his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing will: whoſe vertue and good nature being corrupted by ſo wicked a life, turned love into hatred, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience into rule: for after he had diſpatched the Duke of <hi>Richmond,</hi> Marqueſs <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Southampton</hi> and his ſon, by poyſon, (as by Doctor <hi>Egleſtons</hi> relation plainly appeared to the Parliament; whom he cauſed to be killed in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine parts, for diſcovering the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany;) Thus filled with venome of greatneſs, he made no bones to ſend his Maſter packing to another world, as appeared plainly in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, by the witneſs of divers Phyſitians, eſpecially Doctor <hi>Ramſey,</hi> in full hearing at a Committee. Wherefore, for this &amp; other crimes, he was impeached in the beginning of King <hi>Charles</hi> his Government:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169723:24"/>and though King <hi>Charles</hi> was bound to proſecute King <hi>Iames</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lords death, committed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all the laws of God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; yet King <hi>Charles,</hi> to ſave the Duke, diſſolved the Parliament, and never after had the truth tryed, to clear himſelf from confederacy, or the Duke from ſo hainous a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal. Now let all the world judge of <hi>Charles</hi> his carriage, whether he were not guilty of conniving at ſo foul a ſin, though not of the death: ſo that covering his Lyon-like diſpoſition with appearance of a Lamb, he proved like <hi>Nero</hi> the Tyrant, that in the Parliament of the Petition of right, ſhewing himſelf in his lively colours: for diſplaying the Banner of Tyranny, he put an end to the meeting, &amp; impriſoned divers mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſo that Sir <hi>Iohn Elliot</hi> dyed, and the reſt remained in durance, becauſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169723:24"/>they had been faithful to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and, to add to cruelty, he ſent Sergeant <hi>Glanvile,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Hayman,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Purify,</hi> into forraine parts, to conſume their fortunes, and hazard their lives; calling not a Parliament long after.</p>
            <p>By this time, Sycophants ſo inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Monarchy without bounds, that there were exactions too many to be repeated in ſo little a volume as this: and piety being intombed ſo many yeers, and ſo many pious men ſilenced, cauſed Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and all inferiours, more licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; who by inſenſible ſteps grew Atheiſtical. This was connived at by many debauched in Authority: ſo great a current of prophaneſs was generally for want of Ordinances; which cauſed the People to periſh in Godlineſs. The fault proceeded in both Kings; but eſpecially from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169723:25"/>the firſt, governing by young Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, who had not vertue, but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; this cauſed <hi>Gundamore</hi> (that cunning <hi>Machiavil</hi>) to ſcoff at the Counſellors of State, telling King <hi>Iames,</hi> he was the wiſeſt and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Prince of Chriſtendome, to make privy Counſellers ſage at the age of twenty one, which his Maſter (the King of <hi>Spaine</hi>) could not till ſixty. A jeſt pocketed up by him, who loved commendation and flattery more then truth; by which he was blinded, and ſaw not the hidden flout. This Prince (otherwiſe very much knowing) mued in his Engliſh Reign favourites to the fifth Coat: theſe Nobles being addicted more to pleaſure and delights, then the School of prudence and wiſdome; looking more at their own Intereſt, then the common good, or piety of life, gave ſo vaſt a liberty to their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169723:25"/>lives, as made an abordment of looſneſs in many; inſomuch that ſtrictneſs of life (which our Saviour requires) was imputed a diſgrace; and the vaineſt counted the wiſeſt; the profaneſt, no hypocrite; and a Puritan was ſtiled a Devil: ſo that by this time it was difficult to hear profitable Sermons; the Pulpits being ſtuffed more with eloquence, then zeal to move the conſcience; and the Preachers were fitter for a Stage then a Pulpit. Thus begun goodneſs to dwindle, and vice to ſpread far and neer; vitious being counted the gallanteſt men. But God opened <hi>Pembrooks</hi> heart to ſee the errours of youth.</p>
            <p>But behold! the laſt was Sir <hi>George Villiers</hi> in number, but firſt in vice and villany, as by the former relation he appeared unmasked in his open colours; who mounted the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169723:26"/>higheſt ſteps of honour, and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moſt in the Academy of <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> the Florentine, accompanied with a juncto of <hi>Achitophel</hi>-adviſers, who ſpun the web of all his inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane devices; and had none to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept the contriving, but <hi>Felton</hi> with a knife to take away their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; which hindered further rally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diabolical plots. This man imbarqued us in an unneceſſary war, at the Iſland of <hi>Rees,</hi> where ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brave Commanders ended their dayes, by his unexperienced diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in War; who, though adviſed by <hi>Burrows,</hi> guarded not a Fort: which made the <hi>French</hi> Maſters of that Iſland, after he had taken it; and in his retreat from thence, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his Enſignes in the muſkets, not the pikes.</p>
            <p>Afore this, king <hi>Charles</hi> ſought to marry with <hi>Mary</hi> of the Houſe of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169723:26"/>
               <hi>Bourboune;</hi> and ſent the Earl of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ordinary Ambaſſador to <hi>France;</hi> who, with the aſſiſtance of the Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary <hi>Buckingham</hi> there, diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that overture by the aid of Queen-Mother, with their alluring behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, which drew on the concluſion more then a team of horſes or oxen could: a by-word king <hi>Iames</hi> uſed, to obtaine ends by female creatures.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Dover Mary</hi> was brought, and ſo to <hi>Canterbury;</hi> where king <hi>Charles</hi> bedded her, without the ordinary religious forme of uniting.</p>
            <p>This Queen, ſome yeers after, ſhewed great modeſty, although there lay a pad in the ſtraw: for the Count of <hi>Soyſons</hi> juſtified boldly and openly at the <hi>Louvre</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> that he was contracted before to her with divers witneſſes; and ſo chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged her for his lawful wife before God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:169723:27"/>
               <hi>Holland</hi> of this advertiſed, ſent <hi>Soyſons</hi> a challenge to combat him; but <hi>Soyſons</hi> was deaf of that eare, and never met: a reaſon was, the Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the marriage was too ſtrong, for him to maintaine the truth with his ſword: an occaſion demonſtrated more his fear of ruine, then valour; and that his enemies power abated the edge of his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</p>
            <p>Whilſt this match was a brewing, the Duke aſlayed to defile <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenth's bed by ſome accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which then was found out by the Parliament in <hi>Paris:</hi> a diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtigated him to procure his Maſter to the <hi>French</hi> War, inhibiting the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> marriage, becauſe Count <hi>Olivares</hi> had foyſted into his bed a pocky Courteſan at <hi>Madrid,</hi> in ſtead of his Lady often ſollicited by <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham;</hi> moſt of his wiſdom conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169723:27"/>in ſuch conſtuprations. So that theſe bawdy tranſactions, in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective-glaſs, may bring nearer to our memories the faſhion of <hi>Charles</hi> his Reigne, how ſin was hatched from an egg to a Dragon, to devoure holineſs of life; inſomuch that the Masks and Playes at Whitehal were uſed onely for Incentives to luſt: therefore the Courtiers invited the Citizens wives to thoſe ſhews, on purpoſe to defile them in ſuch ſort. There is not a Lobby nor Chamber (if it could ſpeak) but would verify this.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Iames</hi> dead, King <hi>Charles</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended the Throne, with a diſmal plague of 5000 dying every week: God pointing to us, as with a Feſeu, as a Scoolmaſter, to warn us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of our abominable ſins; if no admonition would reform us, he would ſcourge us with an Iron Rod.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169723:28"/>Yet, in ſhew, King <hi>Charles</hi> gave good hopes to his People of a vertuous Reigne; but finding the ſweetneſs of his invaſſelling the People, king <hi>Charles</hi> paved his path by the ſteps of his forerunner, who reigned twenty three yeers ſave one day: but <hi>Charles,</hi> inſtead of pacing it, ran violently to deſtroy his ſubjects; following too haſtily his precedents direction; which brought him afore his time to the block, the deſert of Tyrants.</p>
            <p>Certainly thoſe times differed much from theſe: for where it is falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly objected, that theſe days are more heretical; I anſwer, By a general ſale of heretical books, then they ſought to vitiate truth with greedineſs, the ſole indeavour in the Univerſities: now in theſe dayes, too curiouſly finding out truth, they miſtake it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, and run upon ſome points of error; which this wiſe Parliament
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169723:28"/>labours to ſuppreſs, by placing pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and learned Divines, (as ſpeedily as they can) men indued with the Spirit of God, through their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: there being a wide difference 't wixt thoſe do wilfully maintaine againſt knowledge, falſhood; and the others, that miſtake the truth. But in thoſe times they ſtudyed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious opinions, being incouraged by the Biſhops; ſo that the Students were ambitious to rake out of the aſhes many hereſies of <hi>Rome,</hi> to maintain their Lordſhips; as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, kneeling at the Sacrament: they uſed arguments of the real preſence of Chriſt, and ſo reverence Chriſt corporally preſent, with the Papiſts; when our Saviour uſed ſitting, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther geſture. From this root ſprang the Socinian damnable opinion, to make Chriſts death an imitation for all to follow, to bury in oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169723:29"/>the great High Prieſthood of Chriſt, and to advance their Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotal Tyranny, and inſult over the People by the power of ſpiritual Courts, which exalted them above others; when Chriſt abaſed himſelf to be a Saviour in his actions on earth; a carriage they ought to have uſed, according to his example: by which meanes, the Clergy were the eyes, eares, hands, legs, and above all, the braine, to ſupport the Kings inſupportable Tyranny. To this head I will reduce their Idolatrous cringing to the altar, bowing at the name of Jeſus, and making Churches Idolatrous; uſually kneeling and praying in them, when no ſervice of God was uſed: and their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, reverence at the Euchariſt, was to no other purpoſe: but to ſupport Antichriſtian Epiſcopacy; what honour was done in the Church,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169723:29"/>was placed on them; transferring the honour done, from the place, to the perſons adminiſtring ſervice: a cauſe made King <hi>Charles</hi> take them into his intimacy, to ſupport his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Monarchy to do what he pleaſed with Subjects property, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, perſonal, and vital; as alſo find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Papacy conduced more to Regality, he favoured them more then Proteſtants: for when the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices in all parts perſecuted the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts upon the Statutes, they were diſgraced, and removed, and the Proteſtant perſecuted and puniſhed, and the Prieſts delivered out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. In which rout, amongſt others, was Secretary <hi>Windebank,</hi> a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Agent to get in favour with Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> inſomuch that I knew divers Papiſts brought out of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and their purſuers puniſhed. This laſt-recited Secretary was a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169723:30"/>Creature to <hi>Laud,</hi> both brothers in iniquity to accompliſh ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>Did not king <hi>Charles</hi> his Letter written in <hi>Spain</hi> to the Pope, ſhew his Inclination to ſet up Popery, if the Pope would grant him a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation to marry the <hi>Infanta?</hi> yea cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it cannot be denied by any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man; if he conſiders fully the bent of thoſe times, he muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by a truth I ſhall utter. When the king came from <hi>Greenwich</hi> with the Queen on a Tueſday morning, a little afore the laſt Parliament, ſhe landing at <hi>Sommerſet</hi>-Houſe, where ſhe lodged, the king arriving at Whitehall a day he uſed to hear a Sermon, the Queen drew him from the Sermon to <hi>Sommerſet</hi>-Houſe; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as a Lord to whom I gave a viſit, told me (when he came not to the preaching at twelve of the clock,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169723:30"/>long expected) in anger, that the king was then at Maſs, and reconciled to the Pope; and ſo this Lord in haſte went after Maſs-time to <hi>Sommerſet</hi>-houſe, and there dined. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no marvel why the Almighty ſent ſo much miſery upon theſe three Kingdomes, and wrought ſuch a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Cataſtrophe to turn the ſpoakes of the Wheel upſide down, raiſing the humble out of the duſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing the proud and high-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>By this, as by a proſpective glaſs, we may behold how king <hi>Charles</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the Fabrick of his potency, or rather the ſtructure of his ill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. For it will appear plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that king <hi>Charles</hi> negotiated with the Pope to reduce <hi>England</hi> to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry privately; therefore it is known to all, that king <hi>Charles</hi> entertained three <hi>Nuncio</hi>'s from the Pope, <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorio
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169723:31"/>Panſano, Signeur Con,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, under pretence to regulate the Popiſh Clergy under the Biſhop of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> appointed by <hi>Barbareno</hi> the Popes Nephew, protector of the Engliſh Catholicks; when the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was to reduce to any union the Proteſtant Clergy with the Roman. And was not <hi>Arthur Bret</hi> appointed to go Embaſſador to <hi>Rome</hi> from king <hi>Charles?</hi> who dyed by the way: and after there was ſent Sir <hi>Iames Hamble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Abercorn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make a ſtep further, I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Reader. After <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s death, the Earl of <hi>Holland</hi> was high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in favour with king <hi>Charles,</hi> who beſtowed on him neer one hundred and fifty thouſand pound in few yeers; and he was no leſs eſteemed of the Queen, being her Agent to receive moneys forfeited, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions given her by her conſort;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169723:31"/>as namely, to free Sir <hi>Giles Alington</hi>'s puniſhment for marrying his neece, twelve thouſand pound was paid to <hi>Holland</hi> for the uſe of the Queen; they ſharing money and delights toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>This made the Kings love of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> not alwayes firm: for a ſuſpition aroſe, as a Devil, to be the bane of friendſhip; which thus happened; ſuch was the intirety twixt the Queen and this Lord, ſhe having ſent Letters into <hi>France</hi> to one Monſieur <hi>de Ierre</hi> then in priſon, ſhe incloſed a Letter unſealed in <hi>Hollands</hi> Letter ſealed; which was intercepted by the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador the Lord <hi>Ierome Weſton</hi> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in <hi>Franc,</hi> and ſent to his Father the Lord Treaſurer, by whom it was ſhewn to the king: a matter made him ſo paſſionately jealous of <hi>Holland,</hi> as he was confined to <hi>Kenſington.</hi> Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169723:32"/>the Queen was ſo diſcontented, as ſhe bedded not with the King ſome nights; and was ſo inraged for <hi>Hollands</hi> confinement, as, till the king releaſed him, ſhe would not entertaine him to her bed: But, as Nature is frail, ſo ſhe flying imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, made the husband more earneſt to perſue her fruition; ſo that at laſt, <hi>Hollands</hi> enemies are chid, and he brought into favour. Theſe are the devices of cunning Dames, when ſilly men, being horn-beaten, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, are cured without a plaiſter: he had better have put them into his pocket. After this, the Queen adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized of <hi>Charles</hi> his lubricity with divers Ladies his Miſtreſſes; which appeared, becauſe he was jealous of a Lord handing a Counteſs he dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loved through the court of <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> at which he ſhewed much indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for a great time. In the mean
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169723:32"/>time, there were not people want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who nouriſhed each in ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that both ſeeing themſelves peccant, one had freedome of Miſtreſſes, and the other of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
            <p>Now I muſt crave your pardon, if I have not obſerved ſo punctually the times; this being rather a Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſody, then a continued Hiſtory, and therefore I am conſtrained to patch up the <hi>poſt</hi> with the <hi>prior;</hi> faults being all of one batch of Tyranny; as <hi>Ben. Volington, Wiſt Stroud,</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hambden,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Corbet,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Hevingham,</hi> were confined, for being faithfull in Parliament. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, for diſcovering the deſigne of a thouſand German horſe, the Earl of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Clare</hi> dead, Sir <hi>Robbert Cotton</hi> dead, my Lord <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Iames,</hi> were ſent to the Tower. The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169723:33"/>was this, as I remember, <hi>Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerni</hi> Maſter-Falconer, found the written project in the kings Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet, it being open; who took it out, and brought it to <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> and ſo it came to the hands of Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> and the other four uſually meeting: but Sir <hi>Robert</hi> had a man would take his cups freely, and, at a Taverne, told it to a falſe brother, who betrayed them all: for which cauſe, the five were brought <hi>aurium tenus</hi> into the Star-chamber, becauſe it was diſcovered afore it was act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>But it is more memorable, how king <hi>Charles</hi> was angry with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the petitions of Right, as he was ſo far from puniſhing Sir <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Plumly</hi> for pulling a Knight <hi>Hubard</hi> out of a Coach, and beating him ſo that he dyed, and to ſhew his hatred to <hi>Hubard,</hi> who was one of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169723:33"/>them held the then Speaker of the Parliament, Sir <hi>Iohn Finch,</hi> in the Chair, that he advanced this <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mly</hi> to be Admiral of the Iriſh Seas, and made him a Knight for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for killing <hi>Hubard,</hi> when juſtly he ſhould have queſtioned him for his life.</p>
            <p>And to ſound King <hi>Charles</hi> his heart, it is probable King <hi>Charles</hi> was in his heart a Papiſt, by the Queens perſwaſion, and her mother; for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter going from the Parliament, he ſent Pardons for divers Prieſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; who ingeniouſly finding this would make a rupture 'twixt King and Parliament, the Priſoners petitioned the Houſes, ſending the Pardons to the Houſe; and deſired, rather then there ſhould be a breach between them, to ſuffer death: for which prudence the Parliament would not let them die.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:169723:34"/>
In both theſe kings times, ſwearing was in ſuch eſteem principally from king <hi>Iames</hi> his example, curſing the People with all the plagues of <hi>Egypt;</hi> though king <hi>Charles</hi> granted twelve pence an Oath through the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to <hi>Robin Laſhly,</hi> which was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved more to get money, then ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs ſwearing: for ſuch a negligence was in the Magiſtrates, ſeeing the great Courtiers garniſhed their mouthes with God-dammees, as if they deſired Damnation rather then Salvation.</p>
            <p>Bribery the nurſe of Juſtice was ſo rife in thoſe days, that right was not diſtributed to the owner: a vice augmented by Knights of the Poſt, very frequent in City and Country. And Lawyers would take ſees, and never plead for their Clients; and ſometimes on both ſides; inſomuch as in a Suit depending 'twixt my ſelf
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169723:34"/>and my Son, we gave fees to one and the fame perſon. Wherefore on theſe times God hath brought on us a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable war.</p>
            <p>Now let all the world behold how king <hi>Charles</hi> violated the rights of Parliaments, coming into the Houſe with great power, to carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the five members. To prove how great a breach of priviledge of Parliament this was, the Author hereof wrote a diſcourſe againſt it, affixing his hand; it being taken in his Waggon at <hi>Banbury</hi> by the kings party; for which he was condemned to die, by Sir <hi>Robert Heath;</hi> and his Eſtate given away.</p>
            <p>I will not repeat how much he hath ſuffered for being faithful to Parliaments, both afore &amp; ſince the acceſs of this; onely I will rehearſe, that being taken Priſoner by the Cavaliers, he loſt four hundred
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169723:35"/>pounds in money, apparel, waggon, and fourty horſes: and likewiſe in <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> at <hi>Broad Choak,</hi> in houſhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuff, four hundred pounds; which was carried into <hi>Langford,</hi> after a Garriſon taken by Colonel <hi>Ludlow</hi> for the Parliament; which he had never reſtored, although he often petitioned.</p>
            <p>Another wrong long ſince he had: when Sir <hi>Robert Heath</hi> had incloſed two thouſand acres of Common, as Lord of <hi>Soham,</hi> one named <hi>Anne Dobbs</hi> was kept with bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Cambridge</hi> Caſtle, by a Juſtice of Peace, a Creature of Sir <hi>Roberts,</hi> to confeſs the Author of this Diſcourſe counſelled her with others to pull down the Encloſure taken from the Common; by that means to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his life as a Rebel; when it was well known he had no hand in it, but then was ſitting in Parliament as a member.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:169723:35"/>
By this it appeares, the king choſe good Judges and Juſtices, which were ſo corrupt. The reaſon was, that the Author being condemned, he might forfeit a Mannor next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent. This Juſtice of Peace was a mortal enemy of his, Sir <hi>Robert Heath</hi> having bought four hundred pound a yeer of the Juſtice, where the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed was Lord, that Sir <hi>Robert</hi> might beg it of the king.</p>
            <p>And if we examine the king of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> brother of Queen <hi>Anne;</hi> the firſt time he was entertained into <hi>England,</hi> what debauchedneſs was exerciſed in his welcome to king <hi>Iames,</hi> to add puniſhment to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily! who both were ſo drunk at <hi>Theobalds,</hi> as our king was carried in the armes of the Courtiers, when one cheated another of the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, for getting a grant from king <hi>James,</hi> for that he would give
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169723:36"/>him the beſt Jewel in <hi>England</hi> for a Jewel of a hundred pound, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him; and ſo put king <hi>Iames</hi> in his arms, and carryed him to his lodging, and defrauded the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber-man, who had much ado to get the king into his Bed. And <hi>Denmark</hi> was ſo diſguiſed, as he would have lain with the Counteſs of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> making horns in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion at her husband the high Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>England;</hi> which cauſed a deep diſcontent between them. And generally the Courtiers were then ſo debauched in that beaſtly ſin, as at that time, in the wayters chamber at ſupper, a Courtier was found dead on the Table, the wine foaming out of his mouth: a horrid ſight to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
            <p>And it is worthy of obſervation to conſider the carriage of the king of <hi>Denmark</hi> and his Son uſually in his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169723:36"/>own Country: for at my being there, I ſaw the old king (as his cuſtome was) to call for the Maſter of his houſhold; when he made a voyage or progreſs, wrote on a Paſtboard what he ſhould doe, and ſo took the waggon to go to his Boares houſes, and eat Martlemas Beef, powdred pork, bacon, or ſuch like as they had ready; and after repaſt, took for a collation the handſomeſt daughter, kinſwoman, or ſervant in the houſe (al her kindred adorning her with all ſorts of wearing ornaments) whom the King carried to one of his Gueſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, where he had not above three or four Lodgings and a Kitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and ſolaced himſelf with this jewel ſo long as he pleaſed; and after brought her home. A fruition made her in much eſteem with her friends, after ſo adulterous a fact.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe it was the cuſtome of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169723:37"/>his Son to ride on a Sled drawn with horſes, bells faſtned to them, which tingled as he paſſed through the Townes; the noiſe cauſed the women to run out of doors: the Prince beholding one more ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then the reſt, beckning to her with his finger, preſently ſhe came to the Sled, and accompanied him to ſome Hoſtery, till he had ſatisfied fully his luſt.</p>
            <p>Alſo their uſual courſe is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane the Sabbath in ſuch ſort, as all the Carpenters in the Kingdom that day work <hi>gratis,</hi> to make the Kings ſhips; and the people go to Church in their worſt cloaths, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no difference 'twixt the Lords day and other daies; who, in ſtead of Godly exerciſes, uſe much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to repeat, that this King ordinarily would be drunk,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169723:37"/>and namely one time (Sir <hi>Iohn Peoly</hi> being his Servant, after an Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at <hi>Wroungay</hi> in <hi>Norfolk</hi>) he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Pooly</hi> to ask any gift, to the value of half his Kingdome, and he ſhould have it. But he finding his Maſter ſo beaſtly out of tune, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a great pair of Stags hornes; for which, after ſo moderate a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, the king beſtowed on him three thouſand Dollars.</p>
            <p>Is it not known to all Germany, that his drinking out of reaſon with his Commanders, loſt many battels to the Emperous General <hi>Wallestine,</hi> which proved a diſaſter to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Proteſtant Princes, ſo that he was faine to ſubmit to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, with much loſs and diſgrace, to the prejudice of the cauſe of God? In which war his brother king <hi>Iames</hi> proved a Coward to back a religious cauſe; for he would not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169723:38"/>raiſe men nor money; yet the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament incited and urged him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: to whom he made this anſwer, He would not give ſo bad an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſupport his Son-in-law againſt the Emperour. Whereas the Laws of the Empire were, If the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour did unjuſtly, the ſeven Electors might depoſe him: for certainly the joyning of <hi>Bohemia</hi> with the Count Palatine of <hi>Rhine,</hi> might have been a chief prop to ſupport the Proteſtant party; which by <hi>Denmarks</hi> fault, and King <hi>Iames</hi> his wilfulneſs, the Emperour got the Maſtery of: though after God raiſed <hi>Guſtavus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolchus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> to turn the ſcales to the united Princes ſide, yet in concluſion, the <hi>Swedes</hi> have ſought more their owne intereſt then Gods.</p>
            <p>Behold, if we examine Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> ſhe cannot cleare her reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>Harry Jermine:</hi> for if king
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169723:38"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> had not been ſo blinded, it had been diſcovered long ago, and ſhe puniſhed or divorced; but the king being guilty of the ſame crime, winked at it; which made him pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind, and count it a venial ſin, as the Papiſts terms them; but ſwallowed the mortal; yet urged by an Earl much with him, if he would not believe the unſutable behaviour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Queen and <hi>Jermine,</hi> if he would go into her Chamber, he might be ſatisfied, and behold <hi>Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> ſitting upon the bed with the Queen; ſo the King and the Lord went in, and found her and <hi>Jermine</hi> in that poſture. The King preſently, more aſhamed of the act, then blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, departed, without ſpeaking a word; yet for all this, the queen was very jealous of the King; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he loving a very great Lady now alive, whom he had for a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169723:39"/>to the intent he might have more freedome with her, ſent her Lord into the <hi>Low-countries;</hi> in the mean while, daily courts her at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> in her husbands and the queens abſence: but the Lord returning, the King diverted his affectionate thoughts to another marryed Lady, of whom the queen was jealous at her return from <hi>France;</hi> ſo that on a time this Lady being in queen <hi>Maries</hi> preſence, and dreſſed <hi>a la mode,</hi> the queen viewing her round, told the Lady ſhe would be a better Miſtris for a king, then a wife for a knight. The Lady replyed, <hi>Madam, I had rather be Miſtris to a King, then any mans wife in the world.</hi> For which anſwer, ſhe was conſtrained to abſent her ſelf from Court a long time.</p>
            <p>Now as all men and their affaires are ſubject to mutation by a heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169723:39"/>providence puniſhing ſinners for ſin, the wheel turns greatneſs from top to bottome, of which I have given you a notable Lantskip in the fraile condition of the Imperiall family of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> who raiſed to a glittering glory by the ſucceſſion of many kings, are now tumbled from the mount of ambition and higheſt authority over three king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, &amp; at laſt reduced not to be Lord of a viſible molehill; whoſe heat of fiery pride hath conſumed into aſhes of ruine their felicity. Let us mark the ſhipwrack of thoſe, who will not vaile the ſailes of Tyranny and oppreſſion; they ſhall not avoid a tempeſt of Gods anger for precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>In this revolution, God had a ſpecial hand, who, when he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to bring this family to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, accompliſheth it not only
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169723:40"/>by poor and weak means, but by his mightieſt thunderbolts of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. This truth manifeſteth it ſelf perſpicuouſly in this Tragical Hiſtory, who have made the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition of three kingdoms ſtumble, by advancing and giving ear to corrupt inſtruments of State placed at the helm; who wept not for our common calamity, but in the tears of inferiours; and therefore I demonſtrate, that never ſhall juſtice be ſo well done, as by Parliamentary proceedings, to ſettle this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth upon a pious baſis, where they proceed in juſtice to baniſh oppreſſion, that property may fall into the right channel, and holy men advanced and rewarded, and wicked puniſhed, to the end that the people may be lulled aſleep in the cradle of eaſe and tranquillity; ſo ſhall love of Governors be in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169723:40"/>ſuch eſtimation, as body and purſe may be at command; for fear poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons a Nation with diſtruſt and hatred; the firſt makes firme and ſtable the foundation of any State, the laſt brings it by inſenſible ſteps to fal and moulder away like a crazie building. Provided alwayes, until the State have a perfect cure, there may be armed Chirurgeons to cut off the gangren'd part, which might putrifie the head, reſembled to wiſe Counſellors, who will preſerve the whole body; ſo they endeavour that taxes be moderated, as the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the pulſe and health ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p>And therefore I beſeech you give me leave to turn my pen out of the Road, with a counſel from my heart not impertinent to my dear country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to profit by the ſtorm paſt, reduced by Gods providence to a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169723:41"/>calme; to make a pious uſe of his great miraculous deliverance. I being a man can ſpeak by experience, who hath been moſt juſtly worry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the hand of the Almighty for ſins; therefore let them conſider that <hi>The chidings of a friend are better than the kiſs of an enemy;</hi> a proverb of <hi>Solomon;</hi> which if we ſhall confide in, we may be ſtiled children con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to good; if not, may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted deſpiſers of the rod: which maxime I illuſtrate the truth of, by the Grecian <hi>Alcibiades;</hi> by how much his baniſhment was more cruel by the Athenian Oſtraciſme, by ſo much more his qualities and worth were eſteemed. The skill of the Mariner is not at all obſerved in a calme, but in a Tempeſt; the wiſe <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> had periſhed, if he had not been in danger of ruine: pleaſures blunt and ſtrangle piety; when ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169723:41"/>moulds the will and humors to a by as of fearing God, inclines us to know our ſelves, and underſtand the end of Creation and birth to the glory of God, and good of our Country: we are not born for our ſelves: Our eyes are cloſed with delights, open in chaſtiſements; in the one, ſin draws more puniſhment; in the other, we ſee clearly our aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as ſpots in a glaſs. We are here on a Theatre for every one to play his part; the tragical ſeems more difficult, by hatred, envy, and jealouſie, the ſlaves of Reaſon; yet in truth, are baniſhed in troubles, when God loves the afflicted better, who, as a Soveraigne, reſembleth the Ocean, which receives that it gives, to the end the revenging juſtice of heaven turn not wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; but the Divel, enemy of repoſe, inchants us in Luxury,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169723:42"/>when affliction imitates nature by degrees from a little to more, and from more proceeds to a humane perfection in piety.</p>
            <p>I heartily deſire you, take this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice above a humane, the command of God: <hi>Be ſubject to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: for they are of God.</hi> Wherefore, I beſeech you, reſpect thoſe ſet at the Helme, whom God hath made inſtruments of our happineſs: for naturally we are hooded, and cannot ſee that God hath done miraculous works: look not upon them as men, but as Gods inſtruments, to execute his will; brought out of the ſhop of his Almighty work-houſe, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his determination; and are not to be laid aſide, till by Gods appointment they turn into the tyring-houſe: for certainly we have great cauſe to give thanks to God for the Parliaments valourous ſucceſs of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169723:42"/>Army and Navy; both for General, Lieutenant-General, Sergeant-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Generals, Colonels, Officers, and Souldiers; as for the Admirals and Captaines at Sea, whom God hath miraculouſly preſerved, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile over the enemies of the State; and ſo let God have the glory, and we tranquillity all our dayes.</p>
            <p>But when I revolve in my thoughte the opinion moſt are poſſeſſed with, as with a Divel, that Parliament and Army are a puniſhment for their ſins, and attribute ſo great Victories to chance; I may juſtly ſuſpect their Atheiſme; whoſe lives I never ſee more amended, by Gods immediate hand on us, to make the omnipotent Father of ſpirits to have no hand in it; or if acknowledged in words, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn not from iniquity, and are not thankful for arriving to ſo ſafe a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as they are in, nor ſee that God
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169723:43"/>is about to mould the world in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faſhion, as he hath declared by his Prophets of old; and ſo, like ſwine, look down to the earth, and not to heaven, to ſee a divine cauſe of a mighty alteration.</p>
            <p>Now to ſhew that the Parliament proceeded juſtly in this war, I will prove it by arguments Divine and Humane, Reaſon and Law.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if we regard the Scripture, we ſhall finde <hi>Rehoboam</hi> the ſon of <hi>Solomon</hi> juſtly loſt the ten tribes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he laid ſuch heavy burdens on the Jews, who declared they had no ſhare in <hi>David,</hi> wiſhing <hi>Iſrael</hi> to depart to their tents; although God had made a Covenant with <hi>David,</hi> that his poſterity ſhould ſit on the throne for ever, on condition they continued to ſerve the Lord as they ought; which Covenant <hi>Rehoboam</hi> broke by ſins, in ſuch ſort as God
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169723:43"/>puniſhed ſin with ſin, ſuffering him to oppreſs and impoſe more heavy taxes on the people, then his father; a reaſon God diſſwaded the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> refuſed God, and would have kings to rule over them, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thral them to his will; but they perſiſted not to follow the Counſel of the Almighty, therefore it was juſt the kingdome ſhould be divided for their diſobedience: or if King <hi>Rehoboam</hi> did wickedly, he could not be ſtiled Gods vicegerent over the twelve tribes; for God, whom Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors repreſent, never oppreſſeth his people but for ſin. When kings ceaſe to imitate God, they ceaſe to Govern or be Governers, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not God; when they are not Gods Deputies, they inſult over the people without authority: for this is an infallible rule (not to be gaine ſaid) in Scripture, that if the people
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169723:44"/>ſin againſt God, and the king do not oppoſe it, but yeeld to it, they are puniſhed; and if the king ſin, and they concur with him, they are puniſhed: ſo that if the Parliament had not oppoſed king <hi>Charles,</hi> God would have been revenged on them. Now when a father wrongfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jureth his children, his love to them is at an end, and ſo is his paternal power; for children are bound to be obedient to Parents, not to be ruined by them: ſo that ſubjects are bound to obey the Sovereign, ſo long as he keeps himſelf in bounds of juſtice and doing right; but if the king would deſtroy his people, they are no more his ſubjects, nor are they bound to obey; but he is a Tyrant. God never puniſhed a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous king that uſed his people well; otherwiſe God ſhould be unjuſt. If God were Author of the conqueſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169723:44"/>over king <hi>Charles</hi> is ſo many battels; who is the God of Sabbaths, that is, of battels; if he were not the cauſe of our Victories, he were not God of battels; in which belief they ſhould give a Deity to the Parliament forces, which is blaſphemy; for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered over the Cavaliers: By which it appears, God ſent this as a puniſhment on the king, and the Victory was not a puniſhment on the Parliament, who defended the people in their rights. Kings are ordained for the good of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, not for their hurt; nor were people brought into the world to have kings over them, but to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorifie God: God is not glorified, when inferiours are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by their ſuperiours; a ſin God highly puniſhed in the Jewes; God were the Author of oppreſſion, if kings had ſuch a deputation from him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:169723:45"/>
This Prince committed a great fault, in adhering too much to his unbridled will; preferring his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on above the good of his people: there may be excuſes in youth, for want of experience; in ſtealing, for the occaſion; in killing, for injuries offered; in adultery, for perſwaſions of love, and heat of youth; in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, for defence: but for offences againſt the Commonwealth, there is not ſatisfaction but a block or a gibbet. For a ſhepherd to ſheare the fleeces off his flock, may be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable; but to flea them, and cut their throates, is abominable before God and man. For kings ſhould have the care of a Maſter, love of a Father, tenderneſs of a Protector, diligence of a Shepherd, to preſerve their ſubjects from wrong: for without a Parliament, kings have no ears, nor eyes to ſee the injuries
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169723:45"/>of the publicke, but by their favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites; who, for to encreaſe Wealth (raiſed from nothing) are like blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuckers, to drain the people, &amp; make themſelves rich. If every member of the commonwealth ought to preſerv the State above his own life, much more a King is choſen Gods vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent on earth, to preſerve his people committed to his charge in ſafety.</p>
            <p>Therefore God took from <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> and <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> their kingdoms, by his inſtruments the people; and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> and <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> both for pride, and wronging the Jews; the one was reduced to graſs with the beaſts, and the other was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown in battel with hundred thouſands. The example of <hi>Attilius Regulus</hi> is commendable; who, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the honour of the Roman Senate ſhould ſuffer prejudice, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his promiſe, and returned to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169723:46"/>
               <hi>Carthage,</hi> to undergo exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. If ſubjects, much more a King God hath intruſted with his people, ſhould have care of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and People; then much more ſhould be take care of the lives of the people.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Parliament ſeeing King <hi>Charles</hi> did raiſe an Army to defend ill counſellors, and ruine his people, the Parliament; rather then the king ſhould ruine the people, firſt they employed the Army to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him bad Counſellors, and bring them to condigne puniſhment; but King <hi>Charles</hi> juſtified their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive advice by a war, to ruine the authority Parliaments; and by this made himſelf an enemy of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. Therefore it was juſt the Parliament ſhould defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by a war, yea ſubdue the kings power, which would deſtroy the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169723:46"/>Repreſentative, which maintained the liberty of the ſubject and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of their perſonall and reall eſtates.</p>
            <p>And though it may be objected, he had moſt of the gentry and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; yet I anſwer, They had the major part of the Electors ſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Parliament, in their purſes.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſome object, that the king had many Members of Parliament; but for certaine, if they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the lawfully-called Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, to ruine the people, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder in the houſe were the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, to adjourn the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from day to day; for otherwiſe it had been <hi>ſine die,</hi> and <hi>ipſo facto</hi> diſſolved the Parliament; then had the whole Nation remained ſlaves and vaſſals for ever, at the kings mercy. And therefore it was moſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169723:47"/>to ſubdue and put king <hi>Charles</hi> to death, as a mortal enemy, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to deſtroy the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth with all his power; for if a member, who hath an incluſive right, ought to have ſentence of death; much more a king, who hath an impoſitive care from God, ought to have ſentence of death: for kings now are not the anointed of God, as <hi>David</hi> was; but by the Scripture, every Saint is annointed; which by the Popiſh Clergy was uſurped to them, and after by their policy attributed faſely to kings, to maintaine their Hierarchy.</p>
            <p>Whrefore we may juſtly argue, that the Author of ſpirits had a long time continued patient, in ſuffering three ſeveral families to be Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents over three kingdoms five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeers; when he raiſed the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral houſes to the Throne, to make an
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169723:47"/>eſſay of their behaviour, to bring up the people in the fear of God; whoſe time was long ſpent in Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and after reduced to a prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and then to a peece, and little part of a reformed way, and not to a total; partly ſerving <hi>Baal,</hi> and partly God; which cauſed Gods arrows at laſt to flie abroad, and ſhot the laſt Prince with a mortal blow: for it is manifeſt, a king could not make a war with his Parliament, till it were ended; and the king paſſed an Act not to end it till all the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates were agreed: and when it end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, all he could do, ſhould be to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict them by a Jury, to finde them guilty; but by making a War, he leaves them at liberty to defend themſelves; ſo that what he did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, ſhould be complained of in the next Parliament after.</p>
            <p>In the war, the kings purpoſe could
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169723:48"/>not be to make them obedient; which is too harſh a way: for in ſo doing, he becomes their enemy; and then they are out of his protection. Or if the ſubjects war with the king, and he oppoſe, they are not ſubjects. A king is not a king, when he makes a war againſt his ſubjects, but he is a Tyrant; and they are not Rebels, no more then when a king treateth with his ſubiects, are they not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: by ſuch a war, he ratifieth them to have a right and power to conteſt with him; as the fifteen Provinces were made by the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in a Negotiation, a free State: much more the reaſon holds in a war.</p>
            <p>How many times did the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment court the king, yea humbly petition him, and treated with him by Commiſſioners, to do divers things moſt neceſſary for the good of the then kingdom! and he remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169723:48"/>obdurate. If he were ſo obſtinate when he was under the power of the Parliament (as in the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi>) how averſe would he be, or rather, domineer over and ruine them, when they were in his clutches! As if a Partridge (being neer to a Faulcon) intangled with his varvels, might peck and tach her, yet would not ſhe yeeld to ſmal a bird; what could the Faulcon do when he had her truſſed: ſurely plume on her, and at laſt wring off her head.</p>
            <p>How many times have the people in this Nation aſſumed the power to themſelves, for kings over-flowing the rules of moderation! as in the times of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond; <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, and after, upon good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, they reſigned the keyes of Soveraignity to the intruſted keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; as namely in chooſing the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169723:49"/>Officers, which of right be longed to the Parliament; and a long time ſince, by intruſion, kept in the hands of the Diadem, but in a Parliamentary orbe; wherein when the great Officers were fixed, they kept their courſe from Retrograda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by their Aromatical influence upon the good of the people; but after they were at the devotion of the chief, by that derivation they wronged the people, and augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the power of invaſſalage; as who in name of the Upper, inſulted over the Inferiour; that all the Engliſh world was conformed to an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible ſubjection and ſubmiſſion, too unjuſtly impoſed.</p>
            <p>Therefore it was impoſſible that <hi>Charles</hi> which had his hands in the blood of hundred thouſands, by his inſtruments, ſhould after that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage be free from Cruelty, Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169723:49"/>and Injuſtice; no more then a Leper can be made pure, or a Blackamore white, or a Leopard clear from ſpots. Therefore I will juſtly conclude, the cup of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance was filled to the blim, for king <hi>Charles</hi> his family to drink the dregs.</p>
            <p>Now if the war of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> were juſt, eſpecially the laſt, when the Emperour tranſgreſſed the laws of the Empire, to make the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Princes to raiſe an Hoſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves, and rectifie what was amiſs, by ingrafting another Cion in the Empire; which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too long in one houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> much more juſt is that of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which hath Legiſlative power, and authority to draw Acts for the good of the Subject, to which the king is alwayes injoyned not to end the Aſſembly, till he had ſigned
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169723:50"/>ſuch Acts, and reformed all abuſes complained of. If the king ſhould retire from the great Counſel, and not ſigne Bils of Right, twelve of the Lords, and twenty four of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, were to repaire to him, to know the cauſe of his abſence; and urge the king to ſigne ſuch bils, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move grievances. If he did not ſign nor come in the ſpace of fourty days, they ought to chuſe a Protector. And if he did perſiſt in his abſence, they might juſtly depoſe him; as appears in the book of the manner and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of holding Parliaments. And this was the reaſon of the former kings removal.</p>
            <p>If a maſter of a Family, who hath wife, children, ſervants, ſtock, and cattel, in a madneſs ſhould go away from his houſe, and bring a force to deſtroy his family, kill his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, take away his cattel off his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169723:50"/>own ground, and burn his houſe, he were a mad man, and fitter for Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, then to be a maſter of a family; as likewiſe a Protector, who ought to protect his people, if he would deſtroy them, becauſe they would have a pious and vertuous govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he is to be accounted a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, no protector.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, The king had a number of his ſubjects, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part.</p>
            <p>But they were ſuch as ſupported a Power would take away the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their real, perſonal, and vital eſtates; which the King might do, if he conquered: if there were not Parliaments, a check on the Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aigne, to protect inferiours, ſuch kingly power would grow to ſuch a height, as no moderation might be 'twixt Mercy and Tyranny.</p>
            <p>I have often heard the Cavaliers
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169723:51"/>ſay, They meant not to take away Parliaments, knowing they were for their good and benefit.</p>
            <p>But if the King had prevailed by their means, they ſhould never have had Parliaments after: then they would have been like Deer put in a toyle, and would have proved in the ſecond degree after us ſlaves; of which ſlavery they were principal authors.</p>
            <p>Open your eyes, yee Cavaliers, and ſee what nooze you had prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for your own necks; when it had been too late to get your heads out, after the conqueſt, and Parliament ruined. Look into <hi>France:</hi> when the Parliament Eſtates were deſtroyed, they were no better then ſlaves. How many of the Nobility ſuffered! as <hi>Montmorancy,</hi> Count of <hi>Soyſons, Bouillon,</hi> and others; and the people generally ſo miſerable, as they can hardly live.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:169723:51"/>
For Bills of Grace, I ſee no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for it; a Prerogative intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only by the power of kings; for people, (when they chuſe one to rule over them) would juſtly be dealt with, and not harſhly, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient; for then the Soveraigne ought to be loving to them, and a father to them. But when the king takes his ſword to fight with his ſubjects, they ought to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; eſpecially the Parliament, which is the higheſt appeal for any wrong offered by the king.</p>
            <p>Therefore it was that our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law allowed every one a plea upon a Writ, juſtifying any againſt the Crown, for taking away of real and perſonal eſtate. Alſo if <hi>Magna Charta</hi> forbids any free man to he impriſoned, and allows him an <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus;</hi> much more life may be preſerved and defended by the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169723:52"/>ſword; for upon an Indictment of man ſlaughter <hi>in ſe defendendo,</hi> it is a good plea to ſave his life in his defence, although he kill the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>If any one defend his eſtate againſt the king, much more life may be defended, by a Parliamentary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which is of a higher nature: if every ſubject, then the Parliament, which repreſents the whole body, may raiſe an army (if the people be willing to undergo it) on purpoſe to defend their lives. All Warrants of peace and good behaviour were made in the kings name; ſo then if the king raiſe an army to murther his ſubjects, he hath loſt to be a defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of them, and hath ſuſpended, or rather loſt his Perogative of Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aignty; for every ſubject may kill one another, when there is no power to reſtraine them; and the king cannot
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169723:52"/>defend, when he raiſeth a power to kill them. The King had two ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities; one as a King, another as proprietor of Lands, Honors, and Seigniories: when he loſt his firſt capacity, the Parliament, which is the repreſentative, in right of the people might juſtly aſſume the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream authority to themſelves, to defend thoſe the king would mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for the people firſt granted or ſuffered kings to have authority over them for their good; but when the King abuſeth it, he ceaſes to be any longer their King, but becomes a cruel Tyrant; and then he may be juſtly tryed in his ſecond capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as a Subject, and loſe his life, forfeit lands and goods by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament the ſupreme Judges.</p>
            <p>And therefore it was, that <hi>Richard</hi> the third, before <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh conquered him, was held a lawful
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169723:53"/>king, and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh attaint as a Rebel by Parliament; but after the Conqueſt, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh his Attainder was reverſed, and <hi>Richard</hi> the third affirmed to be a Tyrant. This declares poſitively, that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have onely power to ratifie and annul kings, and no other. For elſe, by power any one may be a Soveraigne, without the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments approbation: but never any aſcended the Throne, that was not confirmed by Parliament; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in way of Ceremony, but eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially and really performed, by an Act to allow and ratifie the preſent King, or elſe he could not lawfully govern.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the King takes an oath at his Coronation, to maintaine all the priviledges of the people: but when he brings them to oppreſſion and Tyranny, he is perjured, and loſeth
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169723:53"/>the title of a father and protector of his people, and is in the capacity of an enemy to the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>Many examples are in the world, that Kings, when they became Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants have been depoſed and killed; as in <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> among the <hi>Turkes, Babylonians, Perſians, Greeks</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manr;</hi> and he who is an enemy to the Commonwealth, deſerveth to die by all Laws Humane and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</p>
            <p>Kings have augmented their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, and ſo by intruſion have tyrannized over the Subject: for they have in the interim of Parliaments had prerogatives to pardon Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, and ſuch as are expreſſed in the Acts of Parliament; and by their greatneſs they incroached their power: for Kings could not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the life of any Subject, but by Indictment and Arraignment, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169723:54"/>that by a Jury of twelve men, who muſt finde the Delinquent guilty or not guilty; not in Parliaments, but in the interim of them: wherefore King <hi>Charles</hi> his coming with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med power to take out the five mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, was a high breach of privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and for declaring he would break the neck of Parliaments, he deſerved to be dethroned: this was to deſtroy the right of his Subjects, ſo that they ſhould have no property in eſtate, real or perſonal, nor life: for while the Parliament ſate, he ought not to queſtion any: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he could not take away the life and eſtate of any without a Jury, but it would be queſtioned the next Parliament, as many Preſidents in the Rolls of Parliament ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>A Parliament is a free place, where every one ought to ſpeak their mind
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169723:54"/>freely, for the good of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Now it was the faſhion of King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles,</hi> when anyſpoke for the good of the people, to corrupt them with preferment, and make them Royaliſts who were afore for the Commonwealth; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment drawing them oppoſite to the Commonwealth, as Sir <hi>Henry Yelverton,</hi> Sir <hi>John Savill,</hi> Sergeant <hi>Glanvile,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Heath,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Noye;</hi> but Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Noye</hi> ſhewed afore his death a great remorſe for it, to ſome of his intimate friends. It was greatneſs ſo bewitched them, and increaſed the kings power, to wit, by preferment and honors, inſomuch as Sir <hi>Edward Hoby,</hi> a factious Gentleman, at a Committee in the Parliament choſen to puniſh ſome boyes that abuſed old Maſter <hi>Jordans</hi> Gloves, certaine boyes being proved to be the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169723:55"/>of that Roguery, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee debated what School-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould correct them, whether <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> or <hi>Pauls;</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Hoby</hi> (I ſay) told the Comittee he had found out one would laſh on both ſides, meaning Maſter <hi>Yelver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry</hi> being newly choſen Sollicitor-General for the king, to ſigne Bils of Grace; which was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Parliament to be done, when Lotds and Commons had ſigned them afore, but out of Parliaments the kings had no ſuch right. Its true, kings might in interim of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, upon an invaſion, raiſe an Army, and impoſe monys upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Subjects; but this was au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by Parliament; and if he did amiſs, it was queſtioned the next Parliament. This ſhewes plainly, that the Parliament had the power, not the Royalty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:169723:55"/>
It is true, kings had a power to call Parliaments; ſo have the Beadles in the Univerſities power of calling Aſſemblies, Stwards of Courts to ſend out Warrants to keep Courts; and yet both are ſubject, one to the Chancellors of the Univerſities, the other a ſervant upon the matter to the Lords of Mannors.</p>
            <p>We need not fear Darlings of the multitude in this State; every one will labour to be a darling of the people; and none will make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf great, unleſs he meanes to be ruined, and be an Oſtraciſme.</p>
            <p>Certainly to prevent this, it were good to extinguiſh all the print and ſtamp of Monarchy, not to give a provocation to raiſe power.</p>
            <p>The Pretorian Cohorts advanced Emperors at their pleaſure; the Janizaries the great Turkes; but our Army is ſo pious, there is no fear,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169723:56"/>eſpecially being not in body, but ſome in <hi>Irelana,</hi> ſome in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and diſperſed in ſeveral Countries: thoſe who pay the Souldiers, ſhall have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; but as the proverb is, <hi>No money, no Swiſs:</hi> No money, no obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>While the Romane Senate was rich, none durſt aſſaile the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; but, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports, when the greatneſs of the Senate and riches decayed, then <hi>Ceſar</hi> invaded, after he had conquered <hi>Pompey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is to be obſerved, that what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrows Monarchy, the ſame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrows a Senatical government. The Maiors of the Palace at <hi>Paris</hi> had power to raiſe and depoſe kings at pleaſure, till it was juſtly taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; if there be any ſuch power in the City of <hi>London,</hi> it is to be taken away; for they may, by wealth, potency and multitude, do the like
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169723:56"/>to the Parliament: yet they deſerve much to be reſpected; for they have done as much for the good of the State, as any City ever did in the whole world; and therefore are to be incouraged, to have Immunities and Priviledges beſtowed on them by the Parliament.</p>
            <p>I deny not that there were privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges belonging to the kings of <hi>England,</hi> but thoſe are due to him ſo long he is a defender of the people, and a good king: but if he proves not Gods Vice-gerent, but becomes an enemy to the Commonwealth, his Regency is ſuſpended, and he is but a common perſon: otherwiſe, kings might deſtroy the people, and become an enemy. So that his Title is annihilated, and made void; as a ſhepheard who ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his ſheep when he goes about to kill and ſlay them, he cannot be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169723:57"/>called a ſhepherd, but a deſtroyer of his ſheep.</p>
            <p>The example of king <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, who when the Houſe of Commons would not conſent to pul down the Abbeys, ſent for them, and kept them in a room all night, and in the morning came to them, and perſwaded them to paſs the bil, who in fear next day did it; this is no argument to ſhew the power of Kings: it was their obſtinacy to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt the will of God, who determined to deſtroy thoſe wicked houſes, which were erected in a blind zeal, thinking by their erection to make their ſouls ſaved.</p>
            <p>A king is compared to a father; if he would kill his own children, he ceiſeth to have care of them, and is to be juſtly ſtiled a murther, and no parent, to preſerve the iſſue of his body.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:169723:57"/>
Parliaments were to be called e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very two or three yeers, to reforme abuſes in the Nation; but king <hi>James</hi> ſaid they were aſſembled to ſupply his wants, and raiſe money; and therefore he denyed them any other diſcourſe; whereas indeed Parliaments were called for all the members to complaine of their grievances, which were alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed there. And there were tryers of petitions within the Houſe to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether their complaints were juſt: &amp; certainly if there were ſome now appointed without the door of the Parliament to take petitions, and examine whether they were fitly to be delivered to the houſe or no, it would give great content to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for I am confident there have been many petitions delivered, which ought not to be preſented to interrupt the weighter affaires there
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169723:58"/>tranſacted: And upon this, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament have unjuſtly been charged that they would not hear them, when in reaſon they ought not to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred; for many of them might have been redreſſed by Law, or ſome other way.</p>
            <p>Now to ſhew how the preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive was advanced: and that was done by making Lord-Lieutenants in every County, and ſo Deputy-Lieutenants; a device invented by the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> when he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from being Deputy-protector of the <hi>Low-Countryes</hi> under <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Protectreſs; who wiſhed the Qeen (from a form he had obſerved in thoſe parts, from whence he came, for a way that furthered the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Spaine</hi>) to make ſuch; for if there ſhould be an Invaſion or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in <hi>England,</hi> it would be too long to ſend up to the Councel; but
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169723:58"/>it might eaſily be ſuppreſſed by them; two of the Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants having power to ſuppreſs them, by raſing forces to oppoſe and ſubdue them,</p>
            <p>Whereupon, I remember there was a Riſing againſt the Incloſures of Commons (ſo much irkſome to the people) for in ſome places the people roſe to pull them down, and were ſuppreſſed by the power of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty-Lieutenants, and divers hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up; but the Deputy-Lieutenants were after faine to get pardons; it being contrary to law. Likewiſe a Cut-purſe being taken in <hi>Whitehall</hi> in the then preſence, King <hi>James</hi> commanded the Lord <hi>Garret,</hi> the Knight-Marſhal, preſently to hang the Cut-purſe; which was done inſtantly: but the Knight-Marſhal was faine to get a pardon under ſeal. This ſhews plainly that no King can
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169723:59"/>takeaway the life of any without a lawful tryal by jury; <hi>ergo,</hi> he cannot murther his Subjects, nor raiſe a war during the ſitting of the Parliament; for there he is to be in perſon; then the king is leſs, and the Parliament ſupreme. Now when the king takes his ſword into his hand, and departs from the Parliament, he loſeth his priviledge of king in Parliament, and becomes an enemy to the State; and then juſtly his name as king ought to be put out in any Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the Parliaments authority is to be uſed only.</p>
            <p>I am therefore perſwaded, that the adoring of kings hath wrought this miſpriſion and miſtake of the power of kings, which by laws of God and man they have not; ſo that idolizing them hath ruined the right of the people much; The Lawyers alſo for preferment and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169723:59"/>advancement, have given a greater prerogative to the ſoveraignty then was due.</p>
            <p>If we examine our Municipall laws, and all Civil Laws, they are no way juſtifiable, but as they are correſpondent to the Judicial Laws of the Jews, which were ſet down by God, to be a patern for all to be paterned by. I finde no ſuch power given by God.</p>
            <p>And where it may be objected, that God forewarned the Jews not to have a king over them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed what inconveniences would follow of having kings according to the cuſtome of Nations, what ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry they ſhould be in; this was not to ſhew that it was juſt ſo to do, but that their power and tyranny would force them to it.</p>
            <p>Another thing that increaſed the prerogative, and diminiſhed the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169723:60"/>right of the people, was, that the printed Statutes were not according to the Records of Parliament; ſometime there was added to, and ſometime diminiſhed from what was in the Roll of Parliament; and ſomewhat put in that might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to the kings; and put out was for the benefit of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; as I have obſerved, by my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the printed book with the Record. And truly if there were a Committee to examine the Records, it ſhould be neceſſary to ſee the right of the Subject.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>decimo octavo Iacobi,</hi> king <hi>James</hi> ſent and took what was done that Parliament, from Maſter <hi>Wright</hi> Clerke of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the king by his power and the great Lords of Court, made Courtiers Burgeſſes, and ſometime knight of the Shire by letters; who
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169723:60"/>hindred much the proceedings in Parliament by their vote, it being the policy of the Dukes of <hi>Cornwall</hi> in the Stannaries to have multitude of Burgeſſes, to make themſelves potent in Parliament; which now the Parliament will prevent, by providing that the Repreſentative may be equally choſen from all parts.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe it was uſual for king <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles,</hi> if any did ſpeak in the behalf of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty in Parliament, againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, to make them Sheriffs, or impoſe other burthenſome Offices on them; as my ſelf and Sir <hi>Guy Palmes</hi> were ſerved, after that Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of 18 <hi>Iacobi;</hi> or to be reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them ſome other way, for doing their duty in Parliament, as then was invented by projectors, as I could recite divers examples in my time.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:169723:61"/>
The Courtiers alſo laboured to make good patriots Courtiers, as Sir <hi>Dudley Digs</hi> was made a Courtier, and Maſter of the Rolls, who was faithful to the Parliament, and dyed before a Parliament came: this was to draw their affection from the multitude to the Soveraignty; ſo that by thoſe means Tyranny was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and the right of the people waved; which now will be redreſſed and reformed, by Gods bleſſing, and prudence of the State.</p>
            <p>Now I will draw a ſhort Lantskip, by way of Epitome, to examine what good king <hi>Iames</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> have done ſince <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1603.</p>
            <p>The ſeven yeers Parliament was a ſage and wiſe Parliament, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to do much good for the then-kingdome: and as a new broom ſweepeth clean at firſt, king <hi>Iames</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:169723:61"/>granted ſome good Laws: but the Court of Wards they endeavoured to pull down, which had ruined in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite families, upon offer to give the king two hundred thouſand pound <hi>in depoſito,</hi> and annually two hundred thouſand pound; but it was oppoſed by <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Saliſbury</hi> (otherwiſe a very good Commonwealths-man) as too great a thing for the king to part with. And truly that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment took great pains to reform a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in Church and State; but not much was done for the good of the Subject, but great ſums granted, and a good Government hoped for, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in fruition. For king <hi>Iames</hi> ſpent much time in his pleaſures, and much money in Embaſſies, to make himſelf great; ſo that there was ſome good for the Merchants; but Tonnage and poundage given by Parliament, was for Guarding the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169723:62"/>Seas, which was imployed to the Royal purſe onely; ſo that although complained of, the Merchants were at a double charge in wafting their goods.</p>
            <p>After, king <hi>Iames</hi> wronged the fiſher-men and us much, by granting to his brother <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, king of <hi>France,</hi> for his moneth to fiſh on our coaſt; who under that colour took away the very earth and ſpawn of the fiſh of Rotchet, Gurnet, Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Hadduck, to <hi>Deep;</hi> where they have abundance, and we want.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Iames</hi> granted the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to fiſh on our coaſts; and for a ſmal petty rate, the Iſland of <hi>Lewis</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and other Iſles of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to dry their fiſh; by which they have inriched themſelves above fourty millions <hi>Sterling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that Parliament of ſeven yeers,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169723:62"/>they laboured to reform abuſes in Church and Commonwealth, and that the pious Miniſters might not be tyed to ſubſcribe to the unlawful Ceremonies of the Biſhops; which was not granted; but <hi>in nono Iacobi</hi> at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court were divers pious men, as <hi>Reynolds, Kniwſtabs, Clerk,</hi> and other reverend Divines, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about ceremonies: but that the Divines had not freedome of ſpeech; for all went on the Biſhops ſides; a cauſe <hi>England</hi> in all parts after were deprived of pious men, which were ſilenced, impriſoned, and put out of their Lectures and livings; ſo that want of teaching cauſed profaneneſs to get the preheminence.</p>
            <p>The Parliament of <hi>duodecimo Iacobi</hi> was onely for undertakers to raiſe money for king <hi>Iames:</hi> ſome Biſhops were queſtioned, as <hi>Bilſon,</hi> and others; but the Parliament diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169723:63"/>without doing any thing.</p>
            <p>Then was the Parliament of 18 <hi>Iacobi,</hi> where <hi>Heath</hi> was for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; Sir <hi>Thomas Wentworth,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Wansford,</hi> and others, were for the kings ſide; where alſo Sir <hi>Iohn Bennet,</hi> Sir <hi>Giles Mumpeſſon,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Mitchel,</hi> were condemned; and the Parliament ſo diſſolved; in which Parliament, Serjeant <hi>Grimſton</hi> called me out of the houſe, to the Earl of <hi>Bedford,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Weſtmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Vane</hi> dead, to the little Room in the Lobby, where they offered me ten thouſand pound, or 500. a yeer, which I would chooſe, not to oppoſe the bill of the Fens in the houſe. I anſwered, no money nor eſtate would make me betray the country. This Parliament was made voide, and 32 patents called in by king <hi>Iames,</hi> and ſo he pleaſed the people with a toy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:169723:63"/>
Many and divers were convented by the Councel-table to pay certain ſums, or to be impriſoned; whereof I was one, being brought before the Councel when Sir <hi>Albert Morton</hi> waited.</p>
            <p>Then came the Parliament of 21 <hi>Iacobi,</hi> a little afore king <hi>Iames</hi> his end; where were ſome good Laws enacted; the Lord Keeper <hi>Bacon</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Middleſex</hi> condemned for bribery.</p>
            <p>A little afore this, I being <hi>Cuſtos Rotulorum</hi> of the County of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> by <hi>Buckingham</hi> was put out, and Sir <hi>Iohn Cuts</hi> put in, when I had that Office under the broad ſeal; which could not legally be taken away from me, unleſs I had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome fault, thereby to have forfeited the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now there remaineth no more for the Parliament to do, but faithfully
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169723:64"/>to keep what they have juſtly gotten by Gods Divine providence, and his will, in a valourous Conqueſt; to the end that when they have ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the building of the State upon a right and firme Baſis, they may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inlarge the kingdome of the Lord Jeſus, by their indeavours through <hi>Europe;</hi> which I am fully aſſured God hath appointed, and will certainly bring to paſs, that all the world may ſee Gods determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in every climate of this part of the world.</p>
            <p>After this new State is put into the cradle of eaſe and tranquillity, to make it have a full gtowth, there will be nothing to hinder the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment thereof; no titles upon marriage, as in Monarchy, becauſe the power is in the people, and they chuſe a Repreſentative that ſhall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, every two or three yeers
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169723:64"/>making an election of Members of Parliament; that every one may Govern by viciſſitude: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there would be no need of a <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour to interrupt the proceedings of the State, and diſſettle it by eſtabliſhing of new Laws; there will be no <hi>William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus</hi> in a hunting voyage to be ſlaine; no king <hi>Iohn</hi> to be poyſoned at <hi>Swinſted</hi> Abbey by a Monke; nor there will be no beautiful <hi>Roſamonds</hi> to hinder a pious government; no <hi>Mortimers</hi> to entice to his bed and luſt the wives of princes: there will be no unnatural mothers, like that <hi>French</hi> Lady, who killed her own ſon <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond in <hi>Pomfret</hi> Caſtle by the power of a <hi>French</hi> pride: there will be no <hi>Pearce Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſton,</hi> nor <hi>Spencers,</hi> to draw a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty State into their own hands, by ruine of the people: there will be
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169723:65"/>no <hi>Alice Pearce</hi> who ſat at the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and kept a privy Councel out, that ſhould adviſe a king for the good of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: there will be no wanton Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezan to paſs by the Court-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and looſe her garter, to be a means to ſettle an Order: there will be no <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gant</hi> to deny the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of his firſt children, and ſettle it upon his ſecond wives: there will be no <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, to ſend a number of the Nobility to be murdered at <hi>Calice,</hi> to ſatisfie the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable deſires of Princes; nor ſtriving to ruine Parliaments, though it be to his own depoſing; nor no Judges to counſel the Soveraigne to ruine his people: there will be no factions betwixt the houſes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> to imbroyle the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in War; nor no Barons wars, to make a diſtraction in the Nations:
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169723:65"/>there will be no working to have Burgeſſes in Stannaries by Dukes of <hi>Cornwall;</hi> nor no impriſonment of a Speaker <hi>Thorpe</hi> out of Parliaments; nor factions for their private inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts to ruine the publike: there will be no killing of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth in a Chamber, as <hi>Richard</hi> the third did; no alluring of <hi>Iane Shores</hi> to Princes luſtful beds; no murthering of Princes, and ſmothering them, as was in the Tower; no <hi>Empſons</hi> and <hi>Dudleys</hi> to raiſe an Eſtate for kings, by the ruine of the people; no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to make a war to gather wealth, to peal and pole the ſubject, and after to compoſe the war, and keep the money in his own purſe, as <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh did; nor pride to put down the right title of a wife, and ſet up his own firſt, that was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it; no <hi>Perkin Warbeck</hi> to be an Impoſtor, to put by a right title; no
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:169723:66"/>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth to make void a <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therines</hi> bed, to make way for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wife; no chopping off the heads of wives, to make way for other beauties for luſt; nor no terrifying of Parliament, if they do not give way to paſs an Act to enrich his Coffers, as <hi>Henry</hi> the eight did in the caſe of Abbeyes; no Cardinal <hi>Woolſeys</hi> to ſet up their Armes afore their Maſters, to make way for a Popedom, and too too late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that he had not ſerved God ſo faithfully as his Maſter, by which he came to a Tragical end, to poyſon himſelf; no poyſoning of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt by great <hi>Northumberlands,</hi> to make way for the Diadem; no <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſters</hi> to grow ſo potent, as to ſet up a ſchool to vitiate Ladies: nor no drawing of Parliament men from their fidelity to their country, as hath been uſed in king <hi>Iames</hi> and king
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169723:66"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> his time; nor none ſo ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious as to make themſelves Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the multitude, to make way for their own intereſts above the publick; nor for kings to take favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites to overthrow their principals: none unworthy without merit ſhall be imployed; none ſhall grow law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by vertue of Princes humors.</p>
            <p>Surely all kingdomes have a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, as the <hi>Babylonian, Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians, Grecian</hi> and <hi>Reman:</hi> look in the hiſtory of all theſe, and you ſhall underſtand that Ambition, oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Tyranny, and Injuſtice, have been the changers of Government to ſome other way or perſons.</p>
            <p>It is probable that the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God is to deſtroy all Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy in Chriſtendome: for if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with <hi>France,</hi> we ſhall finde they have always adhered to the Romiſh Government, except a little handful
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:169723:67"/>of thoſe they call Reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. How much have they wronged us in our title, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs truly to us! and though they ſeeme to be Governed by a <hi>Salique</hi> Law; yet notwithſtanding they have not kept the order thereof, which they ought to have done, but have foiſted in ſome males, which ought to have been laſt, afore others which ought to have been firſt: and the Maiors of the Palace at <hi>Paris</hi> have ſet up kings at their pleaſure, and not reſpected the right of thoſe that ought to have had it. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting of the holy men of <hi>Towers,</hi> and the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> the true Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick deſcendants, who ever hated the Roman Hereſies: that horrible and unheard- of maſſacre at <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the thirds time of <hi>France,</hi> by the device of the houſe of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> and Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> who was a Witch,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:169723:67"/>and made Julips of young children ſnatched up in the night, to maintain her luſt; as <hi>Comines</hi> doth teſtifie: and <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. turning his Religion from the Proteſtant ſide, after God Almighty had bleſſed him with one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Victories over the Popiſh League, <hi>Lewis</hi> the thirteenths making a war againſt the Proteſtants, to murder a number of them, though it was with the loſs of five thouſand of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of <hi>Erance.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Bouil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> the Duke <hi>Tremelly,</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, changing their Religion; and Cardinal <hi>Richeliu</hi> giving Authority and command in Armes, on purpoſe to deſtroy the Hugonots, though God bleſſed them to be the beſt Commanders in <hi>France.</hi> All theſe, I ſay, and many more I could repeat, will be a means to ſhowre down Gods vengeance to deſtroy that Monarchy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:169723:68"/>
Let us therefore ceaſe from won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at Gods works: for if a Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row fals not to the ground without his ſpecial providence, then much leſs is it wanting in turning topſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turvy principalities and kingdomes: Certainly if this viciſſitude were not, ſin would have more abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; piety, or at leaſt morality, would be baniſhed; and men would forget the end of their Creation, and think there were no God to puniſh ſin, nor reward the righteous; but do as the great fiſhes, devoure one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>This makes me affirme that it is not probable, that God can bleſs <hi>Charles</hi> the now ſuppoſed King of <hi>Scots</hi> from his predeceſſors, if we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the mothers ſide: the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother was proved by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris</hi> to have made abortive her ſons bed eleven times, by help
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169723:68"/>of a Spaniſh Emperick; as by <hi>Will. Murreys</hi> Ambaſſie appeared; who returned this anſwer to King <hi>Charles:</hi> and therefore it was not convenient to yeild that ſhe ſhould return into <hi>France:</hi> and alſo his Grand-father turned his Religion, and was killed like a Calf by <hi>Ravilliac:</hi> his mother, for too much familiarity with <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Jermine;</hi> for the Duke, for fear the <hi>French</hi> Ladies ſhould tell tales of <hi>George,</hi> often mounted on his ſteed, ſent them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France</hi> contrary to the Articles of marriage; ſo that the Queen was ſhut up in the Chamber alone, not to behold their departure; and cut her fingers with the Glaſs windows, as <hi>Duplex</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Hiſtoriographer writes. And <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, afore his marriage, had for a Miſtreſs a great married Lady (it is probable the Prince would follow the ſame
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169723:69"/>courſe after marriage) by whom ſhe had a boy; and when he was Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> beſtowed on the Chriſtening eight thouſand pound: it is to be ſuppoſed he being ſo good an husband, and wiſe, would not lay out ſo much coſt for nothing. When he kept a book, like <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, what bribes that he ſhared, he ſet down punctually; So much received for ſuch an Office, Place, or Honour; and would be diſpleaſed if he had not his part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed for with his ſervants. And likewiſe the <hi>French</hi> Queen, Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſuppoſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond King of <hi>Scots,</hi> was ſo familiar with Marqueſs <hi>d'Ancre,</hi> whom ſhe advanced to ſo high a command, that by his actions, and the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after in her Regency, <hi>France</hi> was almoſt overthrown, and the prime Nobility; and by her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169723:69"/>to her daughter here, there was procured matters of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to <hi>England,</hi> ſince her arriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; who perſwaded her daughter to draw King <hi>Charles</hi> to the Romiſh part (as by many affaires appeared) and got a Patent to tranſport leather into <hi>France,</hi> moſt prejudiciall; which was condemned by this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, on all ſides, <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond from them may juſtly expect not to proſper, eſpecially by his rebellious invading of <hi>England;</hi> for if he had any right, yet his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion, and the Conqueſt, hath juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extinguiſhed his title, eſpecially king <hi>Charles</hi> and his mother playing faſt and looſe ſo often, that no iſſue from thence can either be legitimate or pious, from ſo ungodly a deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>So that if the quantity of battels
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169723:70"/>fought, ſo great a revolution of the State, the ſeveral qualities and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons intereſted, or the long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of broyles, could render a war memorable, this the Parliament hath undergone, and the new Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral finiſhed, is in the higheſt degree of Gods miraculous deliverances; after more then twenty battels in three Nations, and above 300000 ſlaine, and the State changed of face and Maſters; multitudes of Forts taken and ſurrendred; ſo that the Victorious are but loſers, till the State be brought to be (as the <hi>French</hi> proverb is) <hi>en bon point,</hi> in perfect health, after a war that hath continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed almoſt nine yeers.</p>
            <p>The Subject came from king <hi>Charles,</hi> leaving his Parliament in the ſuds, and violently raiſing a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive war to ruine three Nations. It had rather been wiſdome in the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169723:70"/>king to apply to the people lenitives not corroſives: great wounds are to be fewed, not rent; which is the part of a good Chirurgeon; Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratives are to be given, not Purges, to the patient: ſo Kings ought to amend what was amiſs, and not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them with violence; appeaſe their fury, not exaſperate them by a war: for this thunder-bolt, by wicked Councel was contrived, to break forth in fiery flaſhes at an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the three Nations, about the 23 of <hi>October</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Parliament now aſſembled aimes at this end, that as in Grammar there can be no good conſtruction nor coherence to make true Orthography, without the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantive and Adjective conjoyned, which is reſembled to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſupreme authority, now ſettled by Gods aſſiſtance, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169723:71"/>the Councel of State, who will bring mighty things to paſs, &amp; cauſe the annual Officers to nouriſh all the members in their ſeveral callings, that there may be a ſemblable endeavour of the well being of every good Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen &amp; inhabitant, as well as thoſe in authority; that piety may be exalted and increaſed by the Lamps of the Sanctuary, indued with the Spirit of God; that the whole body may be governed Apoſtolically, whereof Chriſt is the Head, without whom nothing can be effected: for if Chriſt be not chiefeſt in our thoughts, no State can be durable, but like a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy foundation will moulder away: That the Electors may love the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and eſteeme and obey them, who ſpend their ſpirits to advance the common good, keep and defend the weale publick in health and proſperity, that it be not hecticall,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169723:71"/>meager, nor leane; nor too <hi>Saturni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> nor too <hi>Jovial,</hi> but in a golden temper. Theſe are wiſe Phyſitians, who cure the maladies, fevers, and deſtempers, that blood may run in every viene of the State to nouriſh the whole body, in juſtice, equity, and right, through the <hi>cava vena, cava porta,</hi> and ſmaller veines; the great Cities and Townes as well as the ſmall; that the Officers and Magiſtrates have not a dogs appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, to turne Judicature to a bad chylos, but to an equall diſtribution of right, that the heart, the courage of the People, may be foſtred in good actions, without reſpect of perſons, but with regrad to the right of the cauſe; that vice and ſin may be puniſhed, with a parentheſis of mercy; that the Republick may have foraine and native commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; that the Land lie not freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169723:72"/>as the Lord termes it, but that there may be importation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation; that Manufacture may be maintained, to keep from the bane of idleneſs and debauchedneſs, that trade may diſh out all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for uſe, ſeemly ornament, and lawful Pleaſure; that the Merchant, the Purveyors of the Nation, export and import all commodities for the good of the State; that juſt Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, Impoſt, Subſidie, and Exciſe may be paid, without corruption and defrauding the State; that Artificers may be able to maintaine their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; that laws may be kept within the chanel of Gods rule and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that potency ſurround not the peoples property, nor wink at the ſpoile of inferiours; that thoſe in Authority regard more the publick then their private intereſt; that the Orphant, widdows, and fatherleſs,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169723:72"/>be relieved, the innocent freed, and the nocent eſcape not puniſhment; and that the Navy, the walls and bulworks, may be maintained in good equippage, for the honour and defence of the Nation.</p>
            <p>By this meanes, the wiſe and ſage Councel of State will undermine the enemies plots, ſo that their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice hurt us not, by intelligencers in Forraine parts, imployed to prevent miſchief to the Commonwealth; wherein the Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> (dead) was vigilant, at the annual expence of 2000 pounds. And therefore I am confident the Parliament frames the State to this faſhion, if time and repoſe, the midwives of all affairs, would give them leave to bring forth to action their contrived principles, in which hitherto they have been impeded, by the plots of male-contents, and by procuring
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169723:73"/>proviſions for ſubjugating <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> the enemies of God and of this State.</p>
            <p>Conſider, therefore, O <hi>England,</hi> that they do as wiſe Phyſitians are accuſtomed, afore the perfect reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of patients conſumption, adviſe not to action, imployment, and troubles in affaires, till reſtored to ſtrength and vigor.</p>
            <p>Wherefore now I come to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how miraculous it is that my Lord General, deſcended by his Mother by the male-ſtock of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> ſhould be a revenger, under God and the Parliament, of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny horrible murthers and adulteries, oppreſſions, fearfull and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wickedneſs, as I have raveled out the peeces, to winde up this bottome, in ſome ſpecial points; but have omitted many this <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridion</hi> is to able not containe;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169723:73"/>which, when God ſhall inable me, and the State injoyne, I ſhall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly undergo.</p>
            <p>I obſerve likewiſe, by his Father, that this Conquerour is a male of that great <hi>Crumwell,</hi> the ſole contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the diſſolution of the Abbies (under Cardinal <hi>Woolſey</hi>) thoſe adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Seminaries of luſt, gluttony, and idleneſs, that I ſaw with mine owne eyes, when I went to ſchool at <hi>Bury,</hi> fifty four yeares ſince, from a well brought up thouſands of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens bones, which were murthered and caſt in it, that the inchaſtity of of the Nuns and Fryers might not be found out. And although <hi>Crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> by the malice of the Popiſh Clergy, was contrived to die, yet he was a Lord of tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent parts, and a ſcourge to ruine thoſe peſtilent Abbies; as if God would requite and revenge his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169723:74"/>death, by giving ſuch an honour to his name and family in after-ages, to raiſe up a <hi>Crumwel</hi> to be Gods inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to deſtroy ſuch a wicked ſtock, which nouriſhed ſuch irreligious houſes, whoſe hands were imbrued ſo often in blood; And that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the three Generals God raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up this laſt, with a mind and body ſutable to finiſh an abſolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt over the Royalty: a work in which the heavens (Gods creatures) appointed him to be a principall Coadjutor, under this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary power; God diſpenſing ſo much ſufficiency of wiſdome, piety, and proweſs, out of the treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of nature, for an accompliſhment; pointing with the finger to every one, <hi>Oliver Crumwell</hi> as a prodigy, to perform what the great Creator reſolved to bring to paſs in this <hi>Stuarticall</hi> Cataſtrophe; for which
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169723:74"/>he is equal with <hi>Alexander</hi> the great; leaving him to ſhine as a Star placed by God amongſt all the military Forces of <hi>Europe,</hi> under the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the ſupreme authority of the Commonwealth, to be a glorious Sun and a <hi>Prometheus</hi> for to bring in a heavenly light for all <hi>Europe</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold more clearly Gods will and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, which will be more ſenſibly and viſibly known after the next years great Eclipſe, to inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten not onely the Cavaliers, but alſo <hi>Europe,</hi> what Gods purpoſe is to act in future ages; in which courſe it is behoovefull for every Chriſtian to obſerve, that he may manage his affaires accordingly, to the glory of God and his owne ſafety. For ſo infallible is the will of God to take revenge of injuries done, not obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſence of times when they were committed, but transferrring
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169723:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:169723:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:169723:76"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:169723:76"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:169723:77"/>occaſions from one ſeaſon to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he calleth the ſinners into recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when they have leaſt memory of them: therefore God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this thrice honorable Parliament the inſtruments to puniſh all thoſe Delinquents, who have raiſed this ſtorme againſt the Commonwealth, to bring them on their knees to Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a compoſition for their eſtates perſonall and reall, and others to forfeit their eſtates for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable malignancy; who now begin to behold that peace is better then war, quietneſs then rebellion, and ſubjection then oppoſition: for it is not ſufficient that the ſupreme authority of Nation do their duty; but as in the nouriſhing of the body, though the head be well diſpoſed, yet it is alſo neceſſary all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers do their office in obeying the ſupream authorities juſt Command
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169723:77"/>with all poſſible diligence: ſo ſhall they be by the States indulgence uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who were divided, and injoy the ſame priviledges with us; and we all may ſit under our vines, and glorifie the God of heaven, who will bleſs and proſper us.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I humbly beſeech the ſupreame authority of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Parliament, to pardon my age, if I have not ſo punctually ſet them down in order as I deſired, being ſhortned by time, and wanting a faithfull, able Tranſcriber, to write cut this Remonſtrance as I could wiſh: my intentions are onely to manifeſt Gods determination in abaſing greatneſs which will not ſtoop to the Government of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt the ſecond per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity, to whom God hath given all power in this ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary world, for the good of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect;
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169723:78"/>To which I add a gentle admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to all Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> to give over tyranny, and ſubmit to the power of the Redeemer and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who hath ſacrificed his life to ſave wicked ſinners; and ſo prevent a ſhowre of Gods vengence impend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is ready to diſſolve and pour downe upon their heads.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:169723:78"/>
            <p>
               <hi>O Ye Princes of</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, <hi>that perſecute inferiours by Tyranny and oppreſsion, look on the works of God ſince the creation, and you ſhall ſee plainely the great Creator will diſmount your glory and pride uſurped over others, yea a power to hinder the Government of Christ, that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Gentiles is ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the election of the Saints, by adhering to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:169723:79"/>the great Whore of</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, <hi>and her Superſtition; who takes upon her the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Son of God, and hinders the converſion of ſouls: turne your eyes back, and ſee, as in a glaſs, what great alteration God hath brought to paſs ſince he made the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The first great Change was in</hi> Enoch's <hi>time: when men were licentious, God turned the ſtream, and they
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:169723:79"/>began to fear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond was in the floud: when</hi> Noah <hi>had preached to the old world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove an hundred yeares, and they would not be warned, God ſent a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> Deluge <hi>and deſtroyed all but eight perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third was an odd number, in the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous deliverance of his Church the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>out of</hi> Egypt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:169723:80"/>
               <hi>The fourth was in</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manaſſers <hi>time, when the Jewes cryed to God in their baniſhment, and were reduced to</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>from Captivity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The fifth was more worthy admiration, in ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Saviour to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſixth was in</hi> Charlemain<hi>'s time, when Monarchy began to ſpread and ſurround the earth to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:169723:80"/>a potency, by priding it over the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But loe this laſt is Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>battical, and gives a reſt and quietneſs to all your pride and ambition.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
